<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="blogtemplate.xsl"?>
<posts year="2023">
  <post id="patent_1" heading="Patent Case is Over. Blog Reawakens." date="5-8-2023">
    <h2>TLDR Version</h2>
    <p>
      I learned of a comprehensive new Hangprinter patent a while back.
      The patent made the community nervous, so we wanted to take it down.
    </p>
    <p>
      We got lots of help.
      I found an awesome lawyer and we presented our prior art analysis to the USPTO (US patents and trademark office).
      They largely agreed with our analysis and rejected the patent's broad claims.
      The patent then got revised down to a narrow shadow of its former self.
    </p>
    <p>
      We are fine with the revised patent, it doesn't make us nervous.
    </p>
    <h2>Quite Long Version</h2>
    <p>
        In January 2022, news of a very broad Hangprinter patent appeared on Twitter (<a href="https://twitter.com/tobbelobb/status/1487143759687176193">here</a>).
          Two news articles were published on 3dprintingindustry.com, <a href="https://3dprintingindustry.com/news/ornl-gains-patent-for-skybaam-cable-hoisted-construction-3d-printing-technology-203113/">here</a> and <a href="https://3dprintingindustry.com/news/open-source-advocates-ornls-skybaam-3d-printer-copying-earlier-hangprinter-technology-203278/">here</a>.
        I collected my prior art in an extensive blog post (<a href="https://torbjornludvigsen.com/blog/hangprinter-is-prior-art/">here</a>).
    </p>
    <h3>Collecting Advice</h3>
    <p>
      I talked to the Hangprinter community.
      Some engineers way more experienced with patents than me said the patent
    </p>
    <p>
        <ol>
          <li>claimed ownership of the basic Hangprinter idea,</li>
          <li>would only be a direct threat to large scale Hangprinter businesses in the USA,</li>
          <li>already affected Hangprinter startups' funding opportunities negatively, worldwide,</li>
          <li>might be invalidated by presenting Hangprinter prior art to the patent office (USPTO) or a US court,</li>
          <li>might be invalidated if the patent holders chose to withdraw it.</li>
        </ol>
    </p>
    <p>
      In hindsight this was all great insight.
    </p>
    <p>
      But the case also caught the interest of a community I hadn't met before,
      the community of patent lawyers who care about or have opinions about open source.
      I had around 20 calls or video meetings with different helpers from this community,
      and around 14 email threads of various lengths during this period.
    </p>
    <p>
      The info I got was a contradictory and it was very hard to grasp what I should expect from the US patent system.
      Many urged me to don't do anything because a poorly executed patent fight
      would strengthen the patent instead of weakening it.
      Many even suggested that the patent holders would win, not because they're right,
      but simply because they're rich and powerful.
      Some were helpful and well meaning, some were academic and had very fancy titles,
      a few shouted at me in all-caps for thinking I could challenge a US patent.
    </p>
    <p>
      I was told by the more serious sounding ones
      that my prior art from up to one year <i>prior</i> to the patent application date was unusable
      due to a special loophole in US patent law.
      (This loophole has actually been plugged a long time ago.)
      I got cost estimations ranging from 30k to 500k USD.
    </p>
    <p>
      In parallel with learning about supposed horrors of the US patent system,
      I tried to talk to the patent's inventors via email.
      They seemed like good hearted people but maybe a bit naive.
      As soon as their company's legal dept was involved the email thread went silent.
      It might have been to protect me from saying stupid things, but it also kindled
      my fear that US patent system might just be compactly cynical.
    </p>
    <p>
      Days and nights of writing claim mappings, trying to get the format, the dated sources,
      the linked proof of every cited date,
      the wordings,
      the technical details into a state that the various lawyers approved of.
      The patent text didn't even describe a sound physical geometry, but the
      lawyers seemed utterly unimpressed by physics, maths and geometry based arguments.
      I gave up for a while, let all conversations die out, I needed silence.
    </p>
    <h3>Doing It</h3>
    <p>
      After getting some rest, I felt like I should at least try to challenge the patent.
      Even if I failed, it would feel better to have tried.
      I'd been working on the Hangprinter Project for eight years after all,
      and the patent stood in the way of the most basic project goals.
      Hangprinter had always wanted to grow to house-scale and the community had always
      wanted to become a web of profitable businesses sharing a common tech platform.
      The do-nothing strategy was so boring and self-defeating.
    </p>
    <p>
      Besides, it was a little dream of mine to clear up a large design space for others,
      like the expiration of Stratasys' US patent 5121329 had done back in 2009.
      That patent expiration supercharged the Reprap Project's potential by removing lots of patent risk.
      I'd dreamt of supercharging the Hangprinter Project as well,
      but not passively by waiting for an old patent to expire.
      I wanted to actively invalidate a broad patent within the field of cable driven Hangprinter-like machines,
      saving us the 20 years it takes for US patents to expire.
    </p>
    <p>
      I found the patent to be clumsily written and obviously overreaching.
      So in a sense it was an opportunity to realize an old activist's dream.
    </p>
    <p>
      I put together a fundraising campaign to pay for legal expenses (<a href="https://www.gofundme.com/f/keep-hangprinter-free">here</a>).
      I didn't expect much. I gave it a single tweet saying "Hangprinter has been stolen by patent trolls. Here's a kind of hopeless fundraiser for those who can afford to help us fight back legally."
    </p>
    <p>
      It got way way more attention and funding than I had expected.
      But also way less than the 60k USD I thought I needed.
    </p>
    <p>
      All communication channels heated up again, helpers appearing everywhere.
      3D Printing Industry published a third article (<a href="https://3dprintingindustry.com/news/crowdfunding-campaign-launched-to-challenge-ornls-skybaam-patent-and-keep-the-hangprinter-free-210324/">here</a>), and techdirt wrote one (<a href="https://www.techdirt.com/2022/06/24/ridiculous-govt-contractor-copies-open-source-3d-printing-concept-and-patents-it/">here</a>).
      Moderators of the 3Dprinting community on Reddit offered me a pinned AMA (ask me anything) session on their page (<a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/3Dprinting/comments/vs3imb/i_am_torbj%C3%B8rn_ludvigsen_creator_of_hangprinter/">here</a>).
      I spoke to anyone who would speak to me, and to anyone they asked me to contact.
      Most often that meant their lawyer, or to people at the company who held the patent.
      Sometimes it meant the "Patent Ombudsman" at the USPTO or law professors.
      I applied for pro bono legal help through a bunch of different programmes.
      Writing those applications took lots of time but I didn't get any meaningful answers.
    </p>
    <h3>Path to Clarity</h3>
    <p>
      Someone asked if I'd contacted EFF (Electronic Frontier Foundation).
      Out of the hundreds of emails and forum posts, this one made the biggest difference.
      I had been meaning to contact them EFF for months, but that plan had drowned in all the fuzz.
      So I sent an email to info@eff.org.
      I was amused to get an answer from a person with the title "Mark Cuban Chair to Eliminate Stupid Patents".
    </p>
    <p>
      After some back and forth I was introduced to the Public Interest Patent Law Institute (PIPLIUS, <a href="https://www.piplius.org/">here</a>).
      We had another go at claim mapping, and we tried finding someone who could represent Hangprinter in the US.
    </p>
    <p>
      It was Alex at PIPLIUS that told me about the famous Gnome patent case
      (<a href="https://blog.opensource.org/gnome-patent-troll-stripped-of-patent-rights/">here</a>),
      and introduced me to the IP lawyer who won that case for the open source side.
    </p>
    <p>
      He already knew about the Hangprinter patent, and had even tried talking to me on Twitter already.
      He agreed to take the case and offered a very low rate.
      It wasn't pro bono (free) but I'll explain why I found the rate to be very low.
    </p>
    <p>
      He obviously knew my budget since the crowdfunding campaign was public.
      Lawyers charge in advance so my basic understanding of game theory told me that I'd
      probably have send the whole crowdfunded sum to whatever lawyer I hired, all at once.
      I had gotten 196k SEK from the campaign (190k SEK after adding Paypal donations and subtracting fees).
    </p>
    <p>
      I paid 4000 USD (43072 SEK at the time) for initial unpatentability analysis, and later a 1500 USD (16834 SEK)
      flat fee for the full ex partes reexamination process with the USPTO.
      He also helped reduce my fee paid to the USPTO by arguing that I should be categorized as a small entity.
      The USPTO fee was 3150 USD (35351 SEK) and was forwarded by the lawyer.
      This left ca 95k SEK (currently equal to 9k USD) of donated money on my bank account.
      More on that later.
    </p>
    <p>
      For 20% of the price (or at a 80% discount) of the lowest rate any other lawyer had proposed (which was 26850 USD),
      this lawyer did absolutely everything possible to invalidate or severely narrow the patent though an ex partes reexamination process.
      Including clearing up the misunderstanding that prior art needed to be more than a year older than the patent application.
      This improved the claims mapping considerably.
      He wrote the final analysis and handled the endless back-and-forth with the USPTO while
      patiently answering my questions along the way.
    </p>
    <h3>Ex Partes Reexamination</h3>
    <p>
      From this point on in the story, there's a paper trace at the USPTO's website, <a href="https://patentcenter.uspto.gov/applications/90015140/ifw/docs">here</a>.
      It shows our ex partes reexam request from October 2022.
      To see the analysis we put forth, see "Receipt Original Ex Parte Reexamination by 3rd party fewer then 40 Pages Rule 1.20(C)(1)".
      Warning, it's 39 pages of legalese.
    </p>
    <p>
      The trace shows that the reexam was ordered in January 2023,
      meaning the USPTO agreed that our prior art and analysis raised a new question of patentability.
      Our application for reexamination was granted.
    </p>
    <p>
      In April we got the USPTO examiner's analysis in the form of a "Non-Final Action".
      I think their analysis was largely in line with ours.
      All claims were rejected.
    </p>
    <p>
      The ex partes reexamination procedure was chosen partly because it's cheap.
      However, it has the downside that the patent holder gets the last word.
      In June, the patent holders used this opportunity to ask if a
      narrowed down version of their claims could be accepted.
    </p>
    <p>
      I didn't analyze the new claims closely yet, since I still hoped the USPTO examiner would reject them.
      However, in July we got the Notice of Intent to Issue a Reexam Certificate.
      The revised claims had been accepted.
    </p>
    <p>
      Looking closely, I could confirm that none of the existing Hangprinters are covered by the revised claims.
      They now covered only one specific design path, building upon Hangprinter.
      This design path gets legally closed off by the patent,
      so the question became if the closed path was an interesting one.
    </p>
    <h3>Result</h3>
    <p>
      I was pleasantly surprised by just how narrow the claims had become.
      The geometrical mistakes from the original patent remained,
      claiming for example that D-anchors always pull the effector along the Z-axis.
      Better yet, the all-important claim 1 had been made twice as long,
      now specifying a combination of the following features:
    </p>
    <p>
      <ol>
        <li>Guy wires stabilizing a suspended top anchor.</li>
        <li>One lower anchor's cables form a horizontal parallelogram,
            another lower anchor's cables form a vertical parallelogram.</li>
        <li>At least one anchor lack positional control, provides only tension control.</li>
        <li>Anchors move up/down to always be in the horizontal plane that goes through the effector.</li>
      </ol>
    </p>
    <p>
      New independent claims 21 and 24 was added, but they share the same features, except maybe
      claim 24 avoids feature 4, I'm not sure.
    </p>
    <p>
      Apart from being easy to work around, none of these features are desirable,
      and their combination is particularly awful.
      So the revised patent closes off an entirely uninteresting design path.
      Let me explain.
    </p>
    <h4>1</h4>
    <p>
      Using guy wires to stabilize the top anchor as described in the patent makes the top anchor into
      a Hangprinter effector in itself.
      Nesting one Hangprinter inside another is needlessly complex and adds many
      points of failure to the design.
      Besides, it was already suggested in the public Hangprinter Facebook group
      in March 2018, so it shouldn't really be patentable (<a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/hangprinter/posts/342461566264009/">here</a>) but who cares.
    </p>
    <h4>2</h4>
    <p>
      There's nothing special about vertical or horizontal parallelograms.
      Any parallelogram fixates rotational degrees of freedom equally well.
      Making all anchors equal to each other is more desirable since it
      reduces special cases and the number of unique parts.
    </p>
    <h4>3</h4>
    <p>
      Constantly pulling the effector towards one point (an anchor) reduces accuracy and greatly increases wear and
      energy usage of the machine. It also limits max speed and max acceleration.
      Having two types of lower anchors that work differently from each other makes new and
      exotic failure modes possible.
    </p>
    <h4>4</h4>
    <p>
      It is desirable to be able to pull the effector in all directions, including downwards.
      There are lots of forces from the print that pushes the effector upwards.
      If there's no anchor that can pull the effector downwards,
      then you get wobbling and artifacts in your print, or your effector needs to be very heavy which will slow
      you down.
    </p>
    <h3>Closing Words</h3>
    <p>
      We have successfully narrowed the patent into obscurity and can safely forget about it.
      I published much less than usual during the past year, out of fear that whatever I publish
      might hurt my case, or contain unsound legal advice, or tempt the patent holders to
      make more copycat patent applications.
    </p>
    <p>
      Despite not publishing, I have been developing and innovating at full speed this entire time,
      except the four weeks i did blockchain stuff (see my <a href="/blog/2022/#polkadot_1">previous post</a>).
      I now have lots of Hangprinter related inventions lying around that need to be published properly.
      I feel like the Hangprinter Community needs
      to secure the real interesting design paths and make sure they stay open.
      The way forward is to find the promising design paths and then publish high quality prior art
      into the public domain.
    </p>
    <p>
      That's what I will use the remaining 95k SEK from the crowdfunding campaign for.
      The title of the campaign was "Keep Hangprinter Free" so I'll put all the money into that purpose,
      even though this first patent case is over.
      I'll make sure we're better prepared next time around.
      This time we were simply lucky that the path that closed was such an uninteresting one.
    </p>
    <p>
      We were also lucky to have some relevant, structured, and old enough blog posts and videos,
      so that we could make the closing path very narrow.
      In particular, Thomas Sanladerer's Youtube videos were awesome for building prior art analysis upon.
      (See them <a href="https://www.youtu.be/Jk4fhQvNoaM">here</a> and <a href="https://www.youtu.be/gPvIHsF13D4">here</a>.)
      Not only did Tom as an interviewer make me explain basic concepts in detail,
      but the hundreds of Youtube comments were regarded by the USPTO as part of the same "published unit", which is good.
      These comments had date stamps and established that some design developments were obvious and commonly discussed.
    </p>
    <p>
      I'm looking forward to continue expanding world of open source.
      Hangprinter is a gift to everyone, and the community is open to anyone.
      Oak Ridge National Laboratory is welcome to join us when they're ready for faster, cheaper and more modern ways of working.
    </p>
    <!--p>
      The drawback of Youtube is that comments is that they're not saved by the Wayback Machine
      (<a href="https://archive.org/web">here</a>), and they disappear from Google's servers at random.
      One of our arguments had to be changed when the Youtube comment it relied on just disappeared.
      For that reason I will prioritize formats that work better with the Wayback Machine.
    </p-->
  </post>
</posts>
