
    <p>
I've noticed that successful open source hardware projects evolve through cycles or "seasons". There's the springtime, when a big valuable design space is opened up (released to the commons) by the OSHW project. There's seemingly unlimited energy and visibility in the space. Then there's the autumn when there's increasingly selfish competition around a waning source of design space/energy. Nothing is new anymore and companies are hoarding to survive the coming winter. Winter is the innovation environment assumed by IP law, investors, and the common layman. Gravity towards winter is unavoidable and winter lasts until another design space is opened up by another open source project.
    </p>
    <p>
During winter one can see mammoths and yetis fight legal fights while huge masses of people are using their products. It's fun for some middle-aged lawyers and economists. It's a dead, boring, and cold desert for young engineers. They prefer winter to arrive very slowly, and I hope this patent case can help Hangprinter stay younger for longer without halting the development or maturing seasons altogether.
    </p>
    <p>
There's also the advice from a famous Swedish inventor, Håkan Lans, that translates roughly to "if you see no vultures around you then maybe your invention isn't all that valuable". A part of me was annoyed by this patent, but another part has worried that the vultures are so few and arrived so late. I guess if someone publishes a video of them getting rich using Hangprinter then we'll see the real vultures. The paper trail from this re-examination might serve as a scarecrow.
    </p>
    <p>
Securing a common technology base with little patent risk was always a project goal. One way to measure the base's success is to count related companies and patents that others choose to build on top of it. So one narrow patent-on-top is a net positive for Hangprinter I think.
    </p>
    <p>
I've learned that we should methodically teach every detail that makes our machine tick, not just the parts that are interesting to us. We should also describe the main design routes that we deem obvious and/or promising. With drawings.
    </p>
    <p>
It's a bit strange since each machine contains thousands of decisions and considerations. The USPTO, at least in our case, seem laser focused on the parts that would fit neatly into high school geometry or mechanics classes. A fraction of the overall innovation work. Grafting the idea of legal ownership onto this abstract, superficial, and short lived part of the innovation process seems quite random from a bogged down developer's perspective. But I'm more than willing to adjust since the reward is legal protection.
    </p>
