<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="blogtemplate.xsl"?>
<posts year="2018">
<post id="hangprinter_project_59" heading="Design Goals and Electronics" date="21-6-2018">
  <p>
    For Hangprinter v4, I'm changing out the design goals, and hence also the electronics and the firmware.
    TL;DR: I'm going for DuetWifi and RepRapFirmware.
  </p>
  <p>
    To talk meaningfully about design goals, I feel like I must first give you some:
  </p>
  <h3>Hangprinter Design Goal History</h3>
  <figure>
    <a href="./bilder/slideprinter_being_built.JPG">
      <img src="./bilder/slideprinter_being_built_liten.JPG" alt="" width="500" height="333"/>
    </a>
    <figcaption>
      Hangprinter v0 (aka Slideprinter), was built just to investigate if lines on spools could be a feasible way forwards. October 27, 2014.
    </figcaption>
  </figure>
  <p>
    The initial goal of the v1 design was simply to prove the Hangprinter concept.
    I was not convinced that it would work at all, so it didn't make sense to talk about design goals beyond proof-of-concept.
  </p>
  <p>
    However, reading between the lines of the potential rewards that I listed in a forum thread at the time,
    one can get some hints about what I hoped for:
    <ul>
      <li>The most compact, easily printed, easily installed and easily distributed RepRap out there</li>
      <li>Possibility to retract its strings and park close to the ceiling when not in use. Could make it popular where indoor area is scarce</li>
      <li>Extreme print heights (> 1 m)</li>
    </ul>
  </p>
  <p>
    The concept worked, and the v1 and v2 designs fulfilled the hopes in the above list (except the one about becoming popular where indoor area is scarce).
  </p>
  <figure>
    <a href="./bilder/v2_filmstudio.JPG">
      <img src="./bilder/v2_filmstudio_liten.JPG" alt="" width="500" height="333"/>
    </a>
    <figcaption>
    </figcaption>
  </figure>
  <p>
    The above picture was taken at the recording of a campaign video.
    The subtitle of the campaign was (and still is) a design goal
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>Print big at low cost</li>
  </ul>
  <p>
    Many Reprappers embraced the Hangprinter concept, but failed to complete their first Hangprinter build.
    In a blog post in January 2017, I wrote in a blog post:
    <ul>
      <li>"It's made to be useful, so it also needs to spread."</li>
    </ul>
    A new design goal got very relevant:
    <ul>
      <li>Ease of build</li>
    </ul>
    Making builders succeed with assembly overshadowed all other design concerns for a while.
  </p>
  <figure>
    <a href="./bilder/First_dual_unit_under_construction.JPG">
      <img src="./bilder/First_dual_unit_under_construction_liten.JPG" alt="" width="500" height="333"/>
    </a>
    <figcaption>
    </figcaption>
  </figure>
  <p>
    In March 2017, Alexander Osika (above) suggested a dual-unit Hangprinter, with the motors in the ceiling.
    This would allow us to lay the spools out in a two-dimensional pattern,
    and could be made straightforward to put together.
  </p>
  <p>
    I also knew that new challenges would face us once ease of assembly got figured out.
    The v1 and v2 machines had been hard to calibrate, and quite unreliable,
    so in April 2017 I stated some new design goals in a blog post:
    <ul>
      <li>Closed-loop control</li>
      <li>Automatic calibration</li>
    </ul>
  </p>
  <p>
    Even before achieving those goals, we started getting way better prints out with the dual-unit than we ever got with the v1 and v2s.
    Here from December 2017:
  </p>
  <figure>
    <a href="./bilder/Olduhp_big_print.jpg">
      <img src="./bilder/Olduhp_big_print_liten.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="889"/>
    </a>
    <figcaption>
    </figcaption>
  </figure>
  <p>
    By the end of 2017 I iterated on this blog that I wanted Hangprinter to be spread and be useful.
    The goal of usefulness motivated some compromising.
    Auto calibration and closed-loop control were made possible with Mechaduinos,
    who also made the build harder.
  </p>
  <p>
    Below is an experimental single unit prototype using Mechaduinos.
    It was never made standard because it was very hard to assemble.
  </p>
  <figure>
    <a href="./bilder/Clsuhp_flipped.JPG">
      <img src="./bilder/Clsuhp_flipped_liten.JPG" alt="" width="500" height="375"/>
    </a>
    <figcaption>
    </figcaption>
  </figure>
  <p>
    The Mechaduinos are also very expensive.
    Up until this point, I had stuck to cheap parts because both myself and most builders I've met wanted to keep investments low.
    Keeping parts cheap had helped the design spread, but using cheap components was not a goal in itself.
  </p>
  <p>
    This might seem contradictory to the goal of low cost stated above, but cost must be compared to that of other large scale 3d-printers, ie thousands of dollars per print.
    Cost must also take raw materials and percentage of failed prints into account.
  </p>
  <p>
    With (human assisted) auto calibration in place, the dual-unit design with Mechaduinos was ready to spread through assembly workshops.
    Below is a picture from the very first hangprinter assembly workshop in May 2018.
  </p>
  <figure>
    <a href="./bilder/HAW1_crew.JPG">
      <img src="./bilder/HAW1_crew_liten.JPG" alt="" width="500" height="333"/>
    </a>
    <figcaption>
    </figcaption>
  </figure>
  <h3>Version 4</h3>
  <p>
    The Mechaduinos with their powerful processors and "smartness" also gave a glimpse of a machine I'd <i>really</i> like to own and use.
    There is a new local design optimum down that road, one I hope we will call HP4 or HP5.
  </p>
  <p>
    Version 4 will not seek to prove a minimal investment concept anymore.
    The new design goals on the block are
    <ul>
      <li>A reliable workhorse</li>
      <li>that people will enjoy using</li>
      <li>and spreading</li>
      <li>for profit</li>
    </ul>
    HP4 assembly workshops will still be a thing, but they will contain less wiring, more automation, and be even more expensive
    than the HP3 workshops were.
    The prospect of better prints and reliability will hopefully still make it worthwhile.
    I would like the Hangprinter community to grow into a collection of people collaborating on a machine they use professionally.
    More on economical aspects in the Bountysource <a href="https://salt.bountysource.com/teams/hangprinter/updates/14-april-2018">
      April 2018 update</a>.
  </p>
  <p>
    Since Hangprinters will often run over night close to where people live and sleep,
    there's also a smaller and more specific new design goal:
    <ul>
      <li>Silent operation</li>
    </ul>
    Meeting this goal requires using nice extruder motor drivers, nice fans, and swapping out the big gears for belt driven spools.
  </p>
  <figure>
    <a href="./bilder/rocket.png">
      <img src="./bilder/rocket_liten.png" alt="" width="500" height="573"/>
    </a>
    <figcaption>
    </figcaption>
  </figure>
  <h3>Towards The Universal Manufacturing Machine!</h3>
  <p>
    There's also a social goal in the Hangprinter Project.
    As I see it, robots are rising towards becoming the dominant power factor in society.
    I think it's important that the people owns the robots who fill their needs.
  </p>
  <p>
    Giving away and selling robots is easy, but having it fill peoples needs is hard.
    I think the best strategy for getting us there in the long run will
    involve gearing Hangprinter (and indeed other designs) towards:
    <ul>
      <li>Becoming a Universal Manufacturing Machine (UMM)</li>
    </ul>
    This UMM should do the same to manufacturing as the CPU did to computing.
    It doesn't have to solve all tasks fast, but it should solve a wide set of general tasks,
      and it should be spread far and wide like infrastructure.
    Whenever you want a physical object produced,
      you should be able to tell a universal manufacturing machine to do it.
    With craftsmanship and quirks coded in,
      designers should be free to solve problems on a higher level of abstraction.
  </p>
  <p>
    Needless to say, the software part of the Hangprinter Project will grow with time.
  </p>
  <h3>Experiments Underway And To Come</h3>
  <p>
    To create the version 4, we'll aim for:
  <ul>
    <li><b>Better main board electronics and firmware</b>.</li>
    <li><b>Belt drive</b>: This will make axes smoother, which will improve the auto-calibration. The belt drive will also be faster to print, easier to build and more quiet in operation.</li>
    <li><b>Line flex compensation</b>: This will improve accuracy and build volume much in the same ways as buildup compensation did.</li>
    <li><b>Ceiling Landing Bracket</b>: Both the ability to home by clamping towards it, and the ability to stay up when unpowered will improve the user experience.</li>
  </ul>
  </p>
  <p>
    Getting on towards the UMM from there will involve:
  <ul>
    <li><b>Tool changing</b>: What E3D develops right now will be useful and relatively straightforward to implement on Hangprinter.
         Particularly a super fast coarse infill tool is important for making HP practical and useful.</li>
    <li><b>Computer vision</b>: Both for auto-calibration, sanity checks, run time compensation, and dimensional guarantees.</li>
    <li><b>Load Cells Along Lines</b>: This will make the auto-calibration and line flex compensation better, which gives better print quality.</li>
    <li><b>Multi-unit</b>: Independent winch units communicating wirelessly.</li>
  </ul>
  </p>
  <figure>
    <a href="./bilder/belt_drive_Osika.JPG">
      <img src="./bilder/belt_drive_Osika_liten.JPG" alt="" width="500" height="375"/>
    </a>
    <figcaption>
      A belt driven prototype by Alexander Osika.
    </figcaption>
  </figure>
  <p>
    Some of the listed experiments have already been started by myself and others.
    Today I want to dive into the first one:
  </p>
  <h3>HP4 Electronics and Firmware</h3>
  <p>
    I won't try to give rigorous reasoning, because the parameters are so many.
    Instead, I will give a vague list of priorities and share my limited knowledge and experiences.
  </p>
  <h3>Priorities. Ish.</h3>
  <ol>
    <li>Open Source Hardware.</li>
    <li>Firmware we can incorporate into HP repo, preferably GPL.</li>
    <li>More processing power (at least 4x Atmega2650).</li>
    <li>At least 4 pairs of exposed, driver-less step/dir pins for connecting Mechaduinos.</li>
    <li>Exposed 3V3 serial pins for connecting Mechaduinos.</li>
    <li>A web interface.</li>
    <li>Reasonable price.</li>
    <li>24V input.</li>
    <li>No streaming of gcode over serial USB, because of <a href="https://github.com/foosel/OctoPrint/issues/450">stuttering</a>.</li>
    <li>Willingness to incorporate Hangprinter software changes upstream.</li>
    <li>Enough processing power to do on-board auto-calibration and line flex compensation.</li>
    <li>Likely to support tool changing.</li>
    <li>Lots of motor outputs and GPIO for tool heads.</li>
    <li>Be compatible with cheap 32-bit hardware (Due+RADDS).</li>
    <li>Do computer vision processing on-board.</li>
  </ol>
  <h3>Candidates</h3>
  <h4>RAMPS+Marlin+Octopi</h4>
  <p>
    Most HPs in operation have this solution.
    Builders add the optional Octopi for its web interface.
    Stuttering from serial gcode transmission has been annoying on some prints, but bearable on new Pi hardware.
    The top speed limitation caused by RAMPS (Atmega2650) being slow is also annoying, but has been bearable in the pre-SuperVolcano era, since melt rates have limited print speeds anyways.
  <p>
  </p>
    The required 5V->3V3 level shifting on the i2c serial pins has been an issue.
    Failure to get the level shifting right on first try has caused burned boards and lots of debugging.
  </p>
  <h4>BeagleBone Black Wifi+Replicape+Redeem</h4>
  <p>
    This is by far the solution with the most processing power.
    It might be the only commercially available 3d-printer solution that can realistically do onboard computer vision processing.
  </p>
  <p>
    This solution doesn't have the four exposed step/dir pins we need to connect our Mechaduinos.
    There have been some signals from lead dev Elias Bakken that we might get our pins in future versions of his new board Revolve :)
  </p>
  <h4>Smoothieboard+Smoothieware</h4>
  <p>
    As far as I know, the Smoothieboard also lack the extension pins we need to hook in the Mechaduinos.
    If I'm wrong, or if you know how to get the servos in there in another way, go for it and show us how!
    I honestly have too little knowledge about this platform.
  </p>
  <h4>RADDS+Marlin</h4>
  <p>
    This was our first idea for HP4, and it is a strong candidate simply because it's the cheapest viable 32-bit option.
    It requires very little programming to HP3's firmware onto a RADDS board.
    However, Marlin devs are worried that merging Hangprinter support upstream will disturb their work flow.
    See pull request <a href="https://github.com/MarlinFirmware/Marlin/pull/9180">here</a>.
  </p>
  <h4>DuetWifi+RepRapFirmware</h4>
  <p>
    This is the solution I'm currently developing for.
    It ticks all the boxes.
    The well written RepRapFirmware, the great support, and all the available extension pins are really killer features.
    See my RepRapFirmware fork <a href="https://github.com/tobbelobb/RepRapFirmware/tree/v2-dev_hangprinter">here</a>,
    and my first substantial pull request <a href="https://github.com/dc42/RepRapFirmware/pull/186">here</a>.
  </p>
  <p>
    RepRapFirmware, despite being most often used with DuetWifi, also has support for RADDS, so users who prefer the cheaper RADDS are not left in the dark here ;)
  </p>
  <!--p>
    Discussions and experiments at E3D last month made me very keen on making a chair of auto-generated support structure.
    The supported model would be 1-3 people sitting in different positions.
    The top/"interface" layers should be in TPU or some other softer material.
  </p-->
</post>
<post id="hangprinter_project_58" heading="Double Lines, Double Speed" date="8-6-2018">
<p>
  I got the chance to test out E3D's coming Super Volcano hot end recently.
  The high melt rate let me try to print really fast for the very first time.
  At first, I just upped the speed, and it looked like this:
</p>
<figure>
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/RrSPoS3iqcE" width="500" height="315" frameborder="0" allow="encrypted-media" allowfullscreen="true"></iframe>
  <figcaption>
    During the longer travel moves in this video, the lines got very slack/over tight.
    This is because the computations that translate between linear (cartesian) and non-linear (Hangprinter) coordinates are not going fast enough when running Marlin on an Atmega2560 processor.
    As soon as the effector moves slower, the axes resettle in their correct positions.
    As all delta printer builders already know; to move fast with precision we need more processing power and/or more efficient firmware code.
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
  <a href="./bilder/High_speed_print.JPG">
    <img src="./bilder/High_speed_print_liten.JPG" alt="" width="500" height="333"/>
  </a>
  <figcaption>
    My first try at printing near 100 mm/s.
    The amount of cooling was insufficient, so I lowered print speed for the upper part of the backrest.
    Even though surfaces are horrible, I think this print shows that printing infill at 70 - 100 mm/s is entirely feasible.
    This chair was sliced with no top layers, so the holes in the seat are intentional.
    The chair is ca 15 cm tall.
    (Forgot the banana, sorry.)
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>
  Encouraged by these initial results,
    I went on to try to to test printing with much stiffer strings,
    expecting better print quality.
  The first layers did look rather good.
  Warning: video is noisy.
</p>
<figure>
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/OIXtI-Ro_4M" width="500" height="315" frameborder="0" allow="encrypted-media" allowfullscreen="true"></iframe>
  <figcaption>
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>
  However, the Hangprinter at E3D has very long lines, with anchors more than 4m from the printer's origin.
  The long stiff lines started acting like springs, and the ringing was very significant.
  The following octopus was printed at a mere ~30 mm/s:
</p>
<figure>
  <a href="./bilder/ringing_behind_eye.JPG">
    <img src="./bilder/ringing_behind_eye_liten.JPG" alt="" width="500" height="333"/>
  </a>
  <figcaption>
    The tip of the nozzle rocked hard around the eye of the Octupus, even at very low print speeds.
  </figcaption>
</figure>

<h3>Adding Mechanical Advantage to A, B, and C</h3>
<p>
  I knew what had to be done, since I had experienced similar issues last summer when I tested the
  <a href="2017.xml#hangprinter_project_45">version 2 with extremely thin lines</a>;
  I had to constrain xy-rotations by doubling up the A, B, and C-lines.
</p>
<figure>
  <a href="./bilder/inside_lineroller_anchor_double.png">
    <img src="./bilder/inside_lineroller_anchor_double_liten.png" alt="" width="500" height="255"/>
  </a>
  <figcaption>
    The line path inside the new anchor lineroller for ABC.
    The purple circles mark out vgroove bearings.
    Upper line goes to the ceiling unit.
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
  <a href="./bilder/line_going_westwards.png">
    <img src="./bilder/line_going_westwards_liten.png" alt="" width="500" height="255"/>
  </a>
  <figcaption>
    The end of the line that comes back from the effector is not tied to the lineroller.
    It disappears out of the left edge of this image.
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
  <a href="./bilder/tied_in_the_middle.png">
    <img src="./bilder/tied_in_the_middle_liten.png" alt="" width="500" height="255"/>
  </a>
  <figcaption>
    ... and are tied together. Knot shown in red in this image.
    Tying the lines together like this lets you rotate your effector around Z by hand to line it up with your anchors.
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>
  Lastly, a little video of the printer running with the doubled mechanical advantage.
</p>
<figure>
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/bkbuvCg6B-I" width="500" height="315" frameborder="0" allow="encrypted-media" allowfullscreen="true"></iframe>
  <figcaption>
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>
  With the added mechanical advantage, I got far less ringing.
  Prints done at 70 mm/s came out with much less ringing than the ~30 mm/s printed octupus depicted above, so the improvement was significant.
  Sadly, my camera broke, and I didn't bring my prints with me home from England,
  so I can't show you pictures yet.
</p>
<p>
  If you're going to try the doubled abc-lines at home, use
  <a href="https://gitlab.com/tobben/hangprinter/tree/doubled_abc">the doubled_abc dev branch over at Gitlab</a>.
  And remember to configure your mechanical advantage and correct line lengths in Marlin's <code>Configuration.h</code>.
</p>
</post>
<post id="hangprinter_project_57" heading="HAWS Replicating and Anchor Template" date="15-5-2018">
<p>
  In preparation of the Hangprinter Assembly Workshop (HAW), I tested out the Hangprinter Assembly Workshop System (HAWS) recently.
  I'm fascinated by self-replication in software as well as in hardware, so I made Ubuntu run HAWS as a virtual machine that copied itself onto a USB stick that could then be mounted.
  Sort of a parasitic strategy.
  I recorded the whole thing as documentation:
</p>
<figure>
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/gVIOwNDe3kc" width="500" height="315" frameborder="0" allow="encrypted-media" allowfullscreen="true"></iframe>
  <figcaption>
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>
  I also did another video where I create a new Hangprinter part in HAWS.
</p>
<figure>
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Ocwx6vzX3C8" width="500" height="315" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen="true"></iframe>
  <figcaption>
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>
  The part CADded in the above video has already proved to be handy during anchor assembly.
</p>
<figure>
  <a href="./bilder/anchor_template0.JPG">
    <img src="./bilder/anchor_template0_liten.JPG" alt="" width="500" height="333"/>
  </a>
  <figcaption>
    Use an assembled mover (effector) to space out a pair of anchor linerollers.
    Screw your template parts down with three small countersunk screws.
    Put two of the screws in the very bottom of the tracks, and put the third somewhere along the long track.
    Tighten all three screws nice and snug before you unscrew all of them by about a quarter of a turn.
    Your template should now easily slide loose, and your anchor lineroller should easily slide onto the screw heads.
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>
  Now, there is a lot more than templates and OS work going on in the Hangpriter Project.
  Yesterday, I did my first successful test print with the Super Volcano hot end over at E3D's headquarters in Oxford:
</p>
<figure>
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/mwf0_VpTmc8" width="500" height="315" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen="true"></iframe>
  <figcaption>
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>
  The deposition rate of ~250g/h is very promising.
  I hope we'll be able to go even faster, as print times currently limits the practical usefulness of the Hangprinter.
</p>
<p>
  For more live updates (and a link to a live stream directly from the ceiling of E3D HQ) do check out my <a href="https://twitter.com/tobbelobb">Twitter</a>.
</p>
</post>
<post id="hangprinter_project_56" heading="How to Build a Temporary Hangprinter Frame" date="19-4-2018">
<p>
  I demoed Hangprinter v3 at the 3D Meetup Sweden recently.
  I could not mount it in the ceiling of the venue, so I had to build a temporary frame.
  Knowing how to whip up a temporary Hangprinter frame is useful, so I'm documenting it here.
</p>
<figure>
  <a href="./bilder/frame_im_talkin_about_rot.JPG">
    <img src="./bilder/frame_im_talkin_about_rot_liten.JPG" alt="" width="500" height="725"/>
  </a>
  <figcaption>
    This is the temporary frame I'm talking about.
    The shape is called a tetrahedron.
    It's very nice for a Hangprinter frame, because even if you can wiggle the individual standing beams, all four corners stay (very close to) stationary.
    If I were cooler, I would mount my D-anchor on top of the tetrahedron.
    It would be more stationary there.
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>
  Bill of materials:
  <ul>
    <li>7 pcs 45x45x3000 mm wooden beams</li>
    <li>50 pcs ca 4x65mm wood screws</li>
    <li>1 small (ca 200x200 mm) top plate sheet</li>
    <li>Your Hangprinter's D-anchor (ceiling plate) and 3 ABC-anchors sheets</li>
    <li>1 print bed</li>
  </ul>
  Required tools:
  <ul>
    <li>Hand saw</li>
    <li>Cordless drill</li>
    <li>A friend to help you out with the last step</li>
  </ul>
</p>
<h4>Step 1: Make an equilateral triangle out of three beams</h4>
<figure>
  <a href="./bilder/bottom_triangle.JPG">
    <img src="./bilder/bottom_triangle_liten.JPG" alt="" width="500" height="333"/>
  </a>
  <figcaption>
    Fixate its shape by screwing down ABC-anchor sheets in each corner, four screws in each sheet.
    The rectangular sheet in the middle of this picture is the print bed.
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<h4>Step 2: Prepare your three standing beams</h4>
<figure>
  <a href="./bilder/standing_beams.JPG">
    <img src="./bilder/standing_beams_liten.JPG" alt="" width="500" height="333"/>
  </a>
  <figcaption>
    1 beam has been cut into 3 equal parts.
    Cuts have an angle of ca 20 degrees.
    Make sure the cut is facing away from the longer beam before screwing together.
    See the upwards pointing arrow in the left side of the picture.
    The beams' overlap is ca 250 mm long.
    Screw from both sides.
    To the right in the picture you see the top plate sheet.
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<h4>Step 3: Screw standing beams onto the top plate sheet</h4>
<figure>
  <a href="./bilder/onto_top_plate_sheet.JPG">
    <img src="./bilder/onto_top_plate_sheet_liten.JPG" alt="" width="500" height="333"/>
  </a>
  <figcaption>
    Attach screws through the top of your top plate sheet and down into the angled end of the standing beams.
    Make the angled ends support each other around a central point.
    This is what gives the tetrahedron its stiffness.
    When attaching the third standing beam, you need your friend to hold it in place, so it doesn't break your top plate sheet.
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<h4>Step 4: Temporarily mount your standing triangle</h4>
<figure>
  <a href="./bilder/corner_pocket.JPG">
    <img src="./bilder/corner_pocket_liten.JPG" alt="" width="500" height="333"/>
  </a>
  <figcaption>
    Secure the three legs of your standing triangle into your corner pockets, like this.
    Don't attach them with screws yet.
    Sorry that I don't have images of attaching the two other legs and raising the triangle.
    You and your friends will have your hands full while doing this.
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<h4>Step 5: Mount your D-anchor</h4>
<figure>
  <a href="./bilder/ladder_and_tetrahedron_frame.JPG">
    <img src="./bilder/ladder_and_tetrahedron_frame_liten.JPG" alt="" width="500" height="333"/>
  </a>
  <figcaption>
    This is the most tricky step.
    Have your friend lift one standing leg out of its corner pocket, and bend open the top triangle.
    Wedge your D-anchor in there and close by putting the standing leg back into its pocket.
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<h4>Step 5: Get the orientation right</h4>
<figure>
  <a href="./bilder/triangle_in_triangle.png">
    <img src="./bilder/triangle_in_triangle.png" alt="" width="500" height="500"/>
  </a>
  <figcaption>
    See if you can rotate your D-anchor so that your mover will hang roughly 60 degrees rotated compared to your bottom plate.
    As long as you're within ca 45-75 degrees, your printer will work perfectly, but you will have to rotate your ABC anchors accordingly.
    When your print head is touching the origin you must fulfill these requirements:
      <ul>
        <li>Each pair of ABC-lines must be of equal length. Use measurement tape.</li>
        <li>The three D-lines must be vertical. Use a laser level or an aiming plumb.</li>
      </ul>
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<h4>Step 6: Secure and mark everything up</h4>
<p>
  Now you're done, you just want to make sure it stays the way it is.
  <ul>
    <li>Secure your triangle legs to your corner pockets with screws.</li>
    <li>Mark up the origin point on the bed surface.</li>
    <li>Mark the position of your print surface on the floor with tape or similar.</li>
    <li>Mark the position of your frame's corners on the floor with tape or similar.</li>
  </ul>
</p>
<figure>
  <a href="./bilder/marked_my_bed_position.JPG">
    <img src="./bilder/marked_my_bed_position_liten.JPG" alt="" width="500" height="333"/>
  </a>
  <figcaption>
    This image shows how I've marked my bed position on the floor.
    The bed itself is heavy enough to not drift around, so it's not actually attached to the floor.
    I do similar markings around the frame's bottom triangle corners.
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>
  Big thanks to my dad for coming up with this frame design while me and Fred were running around him like chickens in the middle of the night before Maker Faire Rome 2017.
</p>
</post>
<post id="hangprinter_project_55" heading="Presenting HAW-Nemesis" date="20-3-2018">
<p>
  Hangprinter Assembly Workshop Nemesis is an operating system that you put on a USB-drive (size 4GB or more).
  It boots directly from the USB-stick, and loads itself into RAM memory.
  The hard drive of your computer will not be touched.
</p>
<p>
  It contains all the computer tools that I use when I use and develop Hangprinter, and Hangprinter related programs.
  It will be given to participants of the forthcoming series of Hangprinter Assembly Workshops.
  The following video shows everything working on a virtual machine (VirtualBox) with 3 GB of RAM:
</p>
<figure>
  <iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/261016506" width="500" height="375" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="true" mozallowfullscreen="true" allowfullscreen="true"></iframe>
  <figcaption>
    The first screen is what you'll boot into.
    If your USB stick supports it, then you can choose to save changes.
    Otherwise, your changes to files will not be saved upon reboot.
    The video mostly consists of me clicking buttons to demonstrate that things work.
    Auto-calibration demo starts at 17:00.
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>
  Watch on Youtube instead if above video doesn't load for you: <a href="https://youtu.be/m2L1S8I4i-E">HAW Nemesis on Youtube</a>.
</p>
<h3>How To Get It?</h3>
<p>
  It's packaged as an iso-archive, available <a href="https://hangprinter.org/iso/HAW-Nemesis-Porteus-x86_64.iso">here</a>.
  Extract the contents of the archive to a USB stick.
  I use Archive Manager for this job.
  Then execute <code>boot/Porteus-installer-for-Linux.com</code> (or <code>boot/Porteus-installer-for-Windows.exe</code>),
  and follow the instructions to make your USB stick bootable.
</p>
<p>
  Pro tip: If you're comfortable with formatting your USB stick, format it to ext4 before extracting the iso.
  It will enable you to save your changes.
</p>
<p>
  Now, reboot your computer and get into BIOS.
  Usually repeatedly pushing F2, F10, or ESC during reboot does that.
  Otherwise, a web search on "boot from USB <i>your computer model here</i>" is recommended.
</p>
<h3>More Help</h3>
<p>
  The iso-image is build from the Porteus with Arch packages called Nemesis.
  Some recommended sources of further information are:
</p>
<ul>
  <li><a href="http://porteus.org/">porteus.org</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://forum.porteus.org/viewtopic.php?f=137&amp;t=5066&amp;sid=5057823669689bb08ad98fb80bbc5e92">The guide I followed</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://opensourceecology.org/wiki/D3D_Live_ISO#Computer_Models_Verified_to_Boot">List of computer models verified to boot</a></li>
</ul>
<p>
  HAW-Nemesis has two goals:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>Bring down the threshold for new Hangprinter users.</li>
  <li>Give Hangprinter developers a common computing environment.</li>
</ul>
<p>
  A test of the fore-runner of HAW-Nemesis, called D3D-Porteus,
  is motivated and described in my <a href="http://urn.kb.se/resolve?urn=urn:nbn:se:umu:diva-122401">Master's thesis</a>.
  It also contains lots of advise for future development that are not yet implemented.
</p>
<p>
  HAW-Nemesis will see continued development as I collect experience from my series of workshops.
</p>
<h3>Other News</h3>
<p>
  The first of those workshops are already planned together with RichRap and E3D!
  Read more and buy tickets here: <a href="https://www.eventbrite.com/e/hangprinter-assembly-workshop-1-tickets-44216520804">eventbrite.com</a>.
</p>
<p>
  I've opened two Hangprinter Merchandise web shops.
  One for Sweden (hope it works in all of Europe): <a href="https://shop.spreadshirt.se/hangprinter-merchandise/">spreadshirt.se</a>,
  and one for the USA (hope it works internationally): <a href="https://shop.spreadshirt.com/hangprinter-merchandise/">spreadshirt.com</a>.
</p>
</post>

<post id="hangprinter_project_54" heading="A Little Work on Line Flex" date="21-2-2018">
<p>
  Today's Hangprinter firmwares assumes no flex at all in the movement axes.
  This is obviously a very rough approximation.
  In reality, all Hangprinter axes act like springs.
  Accounting for this can win us several millimeters of accuracy near the limits of our reachable print volume.
</p>

<h3>Solutions</h3>
<p>
  Some flex comes from line modulus, but adding infinitely stiff lines alone won't solve our problems because ceilings, floors, ceiling unit sheets and plastic parts also flex.
  Very stiff lines are also thick, building more on the spools and making the imperfection of our buildup compensation more severe.
</p>
<p>
  Another brute force solution would be to closely monitor the mover and constantly compute and execute ad-hoc compensation.
  This could be made to work well, but it would add to hardware cost and complexity.
</p>
<p>
  A third solution is to include flex in the firmware's internal model of the movement system.
  This keeps hardware simple.
  Configuration overhead must be minimized by using standardized parts and providing scripted and straight forward instructions.
</p>
<p>
  It would be possible completely circumvent configuration overhead by collecting flex data with force sensors.
  This would require extra hardware, which in turn would have to be configured.
  It is in the spirit of the Hangprinter Project to make hardware additions beyond the bare bones setup optional,
    and solve as much as possible in software.
</p>
<h3>Use The Force</h3>
<p>
  The scribbles below derive how to synchronize the four forces from the four motors,
    so that all lines can be tightened or slackened, without moving the mover.
  A force magnitude can be approximately mapped to a line shortening/elongation by using <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hooke%27s_law">Hooke's law</a>,
    where a guessed or measured <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Young's_modulus#Calculation">Young's modulus</a> gives the spring constant \(k\).
  Note that the spring "constant" will vary with line length in our case.
</p>
<p>
  The no-flex line lengths that current firmwares calculate can be used to calculate a new line length that does (approximately) account for flex:
</p>
<p>
\begin{equation}
l_{acc} = l - F/k(l),
\end{equation}
</p>
<p>
  where \(l_{acc}\) is the new line length that accounts for flex, \(l\) is the line length calculated and used by current Hangprinter firmwares, \(k(l)\) is the spring constant of the suspended line, and \(F\) is the desired force to be exerted by the line.
  The four different forces \(F\) are called \(A\), \(B\), \(C\), and \(D\) in the derivation/scribble notes below.
</p>

<figure>
  <a href="./bilder/Flex_P1_rot.JPG">
    <img src="./bilder/Flex_P1_rot_liten.JPG" alt="" width="500" height="750"/>
  </a>
  <figcaption>
    The mover is approximated to be a point mass.
    The six forces acting on the mover are drawn out in a beautiful hand made 3d visualization.
    It is not true that we <i>must</i> set one of \([ABCD]\) fixed.
    That is just one of many possible ways to constrain the system.
    Setting \(D=|\vec{D}|\) to be constant was just the most useful constraint I could come up with.
    Note that \(m\vec{a}\) will not be zero during a print, since the mover will be moving around.
    It is however easy to re-introduce into the calculations below, right beside \(m\vec{g}\) and \(\vec{D}\).
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
  <a href="./bilder/Flex_P2_rot.JPG">
  <img src="./bilder/Flex_P2_rot_liten.JPG" alt="" width="500" height="750" />
  </a>
  <figcaption>
    Thanks to my professors for drilling me in manual Gaussian elimination.
    I never thought I would get to use it for something actually useful.
    Maybe I shouldn't use it.
    There's always <a href="http://www.sympy.org/en/index.html">sympy</a>.
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
  <a href="./bilder/Flex_P3_rot.JPG">
  <img src="./bilder/Flex_P3_rot_liten.JPG" alt="" width="500" height="750" />
  </a>
  <figcaption>
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
  <a href="./bilder/Flex_P4_rot.JPG">
  <img src="./bilder/Flex_P4_rot_liten.JPG" alt="" width="500" height="750" />
  </a>
  <figcaption>
    There are our expressions for the magnitudes of the (zero-acceleration-case) force magnitudes \(A\), \(B\), and \(C\).
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>
  Lots of divisions. Probably not simple enough to be done on a Atmel2560.
  So... What to do?
</p>
<p>
  As my professors always told me:
</p>
<p>
  "Taylor expand, my good boy.
  Taylor expand for the sake of glory and honor!
  Taylor expand, and use only the first two terms, because everything ... Yes! <i>EVERYTHING</i> worth fighting for can be approximated to be perfectly linear!
  I tell you, boy, if you ever ever feel doubt in your heart, just Taylor expand, and your problems will all be cake."
</p>
<p>
  Ok, they didn't quite say it like that, and maybe we should use three terms, but I'll save you the expansion for another post.
  If you're so excited right now that you want to Taylor expand yourself: do it around the origin, and remember that
</p>
$$
\begin{align}
  a_x &amp;= \phantom{\text{ANCHOR_A_X}} - x,\\
  a_y &amp;= \text{ANCHOR_A_Y} - y,\\
  a_z &amp;= \text{ANCHOR_A_Z} - z,
\end{align}
$$
<p>
  where ANCHOR_A_X is non-existent by convention,
        ANCHOR_A_Y is the y-coordinate of your A-anchor,
        ANCHOR_A_Z is the z-coordinate of our A-anchor,
        and \((x, y, z)\) is the position of your mover relative to the origin.
</p>
<p>
  Also remember to handle the cases when denominators are zero in a graceful way.
  Fancy new 32-bit CPUs can probably compute the full expressions, but they can't handle division by zero.
</p>
<p>
  Best regards,
</p>
</post>

<post id="hangprinter_project_53" heading="Consequences of Miscalibrating Anchor Positions" date="28-1-2018">
<p>
  I made a script recently, to get learn how a Hangprinter axis with bad anchor positions behaves.
  The script itself is <a href="http://vitana.se/opr3d/tbear/scripts/calibration_errors.py">here</a>.
</p>
  <h4>The Quick Take-Away:</h4>
<p>
  Moving directly from/towards an anchor gives small errors, almost regardless of calibration errors.
</p>
  <h4>The Details:</h4>
<p>
  Four plots are shown below.
  Only the XY axes are shown, but the results are similar in three dimensions.
  Line length errors in different XY-positions are shown with color codes.
  They are normalized so that the error in the origin is 0 in all plots.
  In negative areas, the mis-calibrated axis will over-tighten.
  In positive areas, the mis-calibrated axis will let out too much line.
  Click the plots to get larger versions.
</p>
<figure>
  <a href="./bilder/anchor_config_at_ccw_angle.png">
    <img src="./bilder/anchor_config_at_ccw_angle_liten.png" alt="" width="500" height="266" />
  </a>
  <figcaption>
    In this plot, the anchor is located at (-700, 700).
    The black arrow shows a measurement error of (-97, -97), so the machine has been configured with anchor locations (-797, 603).
    In the point (-500,0), this mis-calibrated axis will end up with 65 mm too short lines.
    In (0, 500) however, it ends up with 65 mm too long lines.
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
  <a href="./bilder/anchor_config_too_far.png">
    <img src="./bilder/anchor_config_too_far_liten.png" alt="" width="500" height="266" />
  </a>
  <figcaption>
    Anchor location: (-700, 700)<br />
    Measurement error: (-99, 99)<br />
    Configured anchor location: (-799, 799)<br />
    Error at (-500,0): 15 mm too tight<br />
    Error at (0,500): 15 mm too tight
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
  <a href="./bilder/anchor_config_at_cw_angle.png">
    <img src="./bilder/anchor_config_at_cw_angle_liten.png" alt="" width="500" height="266" />
  </a>
  <figcaption>
    Anchor location: (-700, 700)<br />
    Measurement error: (98, 99)<br />
    Configured anchor location: (-602, 799)<br />
    Error at (-500,0): 67 mm too long <br />
    Error at (0,500): 66 mm too tight
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
  <a href="./bilder/anchor_config_too_close.png">
    <img src="./bilder/anchor_config_too_close_liten.png" alt="" width="500" height="266" />
  </a>
  <figcaption>
    Anchor location: (-700, 700)<br />
    Measurement error: (98, -99)<br />
    Configured anchor location: (-602, 601)<br />
    Error at (-500,0): 21 mm too long <br />
    Error at (0,500): 22 mm too long
  </figcaption>
</figure>
</post>

<post id="hangprinter_project_52" heading="New Extruder Holder Bracket" date="18-1-2018">
<p>
  I've converted the <code>extruder_holder</code> bracket to be ziptie based like the rest of the mover:
</p>
<figure>
  <a href="./bilder/extruder_holder_render.png">
    <img src="./bilder/extruder_holder_render_liten.png" alt="" width="500" height="269" />
  </a>
  <figcaption>
    Render of the new <code>extruder_holder</code>.
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>
  It is a great deal sturdier than it's screw-clamping predecessor.
  I tested lots of little tweaks to find the stiffest solution around all axes.
</p>
<figure>
  <a href="./bilder/Four_extruder_holders_on_a_mover.JPG">
    <img src="./bilder/Four_extruder_holders_on_a_mover_liten.JPG" alt="" width="500" height="334" />
  </a>
  <figcaption>
    Four slightly different extruder holders lined up for flex testing.
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>
  The motor was possible to tilt downwards no matter how I changed the model it seemed.
  The winning tweak turned out to be adding a third ziptie first.
  Like this:
</p>
<figure>
  <a  href="./bilder/Third_ziptie.JPG">
    <img src="./bilder/Third_ziptie_liten.JPG" alt="" width="500" height="334" />
  </a>
  <figcaption>
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>
  And to tighten the third ziptie with a wedge.
  Like this:
</p>
<figure>
  <a  href="./bilder/Wedging_ziptie.JPG">
    <img src="./bilder/Wedging_ziptie_liten.JPG" alt="" width="500" height="334" />
  </a>
  <figcaption>
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>
  The end result is dead sturdy and looks like this:
</p>
<figure>
  <a  href="./bilder/Ziptie_extruder_holder.JPG">
    <img src="./bilder/Ziptie_extruder_holder_liten.JPG" alt="" width="500" height="334" />
  </a>
  <figcaption>
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>
  All new files and are published to the working branch of the repo: <a href="https://github.com/tobbelobb/hangprinter/tree/Openscad_version_3">Openscad_version_3</a>.
</p>
</post>

<post id="hangprinter_project_51" heading="Ziptie Mover" date="3-1-2018">
<p>
  I've implemented Tom's suggestion to use zipties on the mover corners.
</p>

<figure>
  <a href="./bilder/Ziptie_wood_mover_3.JPG">
    <img src="./bilder/Ziptie_wood_mover_3_liten.JPG" alt="" width="500" height="334" />
  </a>
  <figcaption>
    Ziptied mover.
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>
  Using zipties in stead of screws has some advantages.
</p>
<ul>
  <li>Works with beams of different widths (currently 12.5 to 17.5 mm). </li>
  <li>Does not rely on flexing fragile printed parts. </li>
  <li>Saves some weight.</li>
</ul>
<p>I also find it easier to assemble since there are no fiddling with small screws and nuts. </p>
<figure>
  <a href="./bilder/Ziptie_mover_corner_1.JPG">
    <img src="./bilder/Ziptie_mover_corner_1_liten.JPG" alt="" width="500" height="334" />
  </a>
  <figcaption>
    Ziptied mover corner.
    The zipties' heads wrap around the sharp corner of the wooden beam.
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
  <a href="./bilder/Ziptie_mover_corner_2.JPG">
    <img src="./bilder/Ziptie_mover_corner_2_liten.JPG" alt="" width="500" height="334" />
  </a>
  <figcaption>
  Zipties of width 4 mm gives the most sturdy mover, but I've found sizes down to 2.4 mm (like in this picture) to work well.
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>
  For wooden movers, I've also thrown away the old beam_clamp.
  It's both more sturdy and lighter to just clamp the crossbeam with a little M3 screw and nut.
</p>
<figure>
  <a href="./bilder/Beam_clamping.JPG">
    <img src="./bilder/Beam_clamping_liten.JPG" alt="" width="500" height="334" />
  </a>
  <figcaption>
    Note that I pre-drilled 3.2 mm holes before inserting the M3 screw.
    I use washers on both sides of the hole because the pine wood is so soft.
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>
  These two improvements combined save ca 60 g of weight compared to the previous mover.
</p>
<p>
  I've also added a little nutlock to beam_slider, to make it easier to tighten/untighten with one hand.
</p>
<figure>
  <a href="./bilder/Beam_slider_nutlock.png">
    <img src="./bilder/Beam_slider_nutlock_liten.png" alt="" width="500" height="320" />
  </a>
  <figcaption>
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>
  More improvements inspired by what I learned in Hamburg is in the pipeline.
  Happy new year!
</p>
</post>

<hr />
<h3>2017</h3>
<hr />
<br /><br /><br />

<oldpost id="hangprinter_project_50" heading="The Why Again" date="7-12-2017">
<p>
  This is the 50'th Hangprinter blog post, and I think it's a good opportunity to elaborate on why I develop Hangprinters.
  <a href="2017.html#hangprinter_project_50">Read more...</a>
</p>
<br /><br /><br />
</oldpost>

<oldpost id="hangprinter_project_49" heading="Time for Clones" date="15-11-2017">
<p>
  It's been a busy month and the next one will be busy too.
  I've helped fredrudolf build a v3.3 (aka HP3).
  We're preparing a live demo at Maker Faire Rome (Dec 1-3).
  After that, I will help <a href="https://toms3d.org/">Tom</a> create a video series on Hangprinter.
  <a href="2017.html#hangprinter_project_49">Read more...</a>
</p>
<br /><br /><br />
</oldpost>

<oldpost id="hangprinter_project_48" heading="Version 3.3 In The Making" date="14-10-2017">
<p>
  It's been a month of very technical development.
  I feel like I'm searching for the version 3.3 among a forest of new ideas and insights.
  <a href="2017.html#hangprinter_project_48">Read more...</a>
</p>
<br /><br /><br />
</oldpost>

<oldpost id="hangprinter_project_47" heading="Benchy, Videos and Some New Code" date="12-9-2017">
<p>
  First Hangprinted Benchy:
  <a href="2017.html#hangprinter_project_47">Read more...</a>
</p>
<br /><br /><br />
</oldpost>

<oldpost id="hangprinter_project_46" heading="Version 3.2 Overview" date="7-8-2017">
<p>
  The Hangprinter v3 has developed very quickly recently.
  We've been developing so intensely, we almost forgot to print a Benchy with the current prototype, called v3.2.
  <a href="2017.html#hangprinter_project_46">Read more...</a>
</p>
<br /><br /><br />
</oldpost>

<oldpost id="hangprinter_project_45" heading="Closed Loop Doing its Job and Sstruder v2 Pic" date="6-7-2017">
<p>
  This video shows how the closed loop ABC axes act like springs when hot end meets an obstacle.
  <a href="2017.html#hangprinter_project_45">Read more...</a>
</p>
<br /><br /><br />
</oldpost>

<oldpost id="hangprinter_project_44" heading="Working on Auto Calibration and Reliability" date="3-7-2017">
<p>
  I put together a closed loop single unit Hangprinter with pancake steppers recently.
  The following video shows that it can run upwards along the D-line at 26.6 mm/s.
  <a href="2017.html#hangprinter_project_44">Read more...</a>
</p>
<br /><br /><br />
</oldpost>

<oldpost id="hangprinter_project_43" heading="Walking the Line" date="4-6-2017">
<p>
  Following up on what I planned 35 days ago:
  "When the version 3 is up and running, I will focus my dev time on adding
  closed loop control,
  auto calibration
  and DC motors, in that order.
  <a href="2017.html#hangprinter_project_43">Read more...</a>
</p>
<br /><br /><br />
</oldpost>

<oldpost id="hangprinter_project_42" heading="Experimental Dual Unit Designs" date="30-4-2017">
<p>
  The Hangprinter Hackathon at Bitraf produced some technical progress.
  <a href="2017.html#hangprinter_project_42">Read more...</a>
</p>
<br /><br /><br />
</oldpost>

<oldpost id="hangprinter_project_41" heading="Other People's Hangprinter Builds" date="25-4-2017">
<p>
  This beauty was posted by Mario Lucas <a href="https://twitter.com/l_k3/status/848151053526806529">here</a>.
  This impressive bottom plate was posted by
  Jonathan Bahrs
  <a href="https://www.facebook.com/photo.php?fbid=10154512094258325&amp;set=g.176856636157837&amp;type=1&amp;theater">here</a>.
  <a href="2017.html#hangprinter_project_41">Read more...</a>
</p>
<br /><br /><br />
</oldpost>

<oldpost id="hangprinter_project_40" heading="Babel Tower Time Lapse" date="15-4-2017">
<p>
  To recharge before the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/bitraf/events/239151727/">Hangprinter Hackathon</a> in Oslo next weekend,
  I threw together a Babel Tower time lapse.
  <a href="2017.html#hangprinter_project_40">Read more...</a>
</p>
<br /><br /><br />
</oldpost>

<oldpost id="hangprinter_project_39" heading="First Pull Request Merged" date="4-4-2017">
<p>
  The Hangprinter repo on has had its first merged pull request!
  Committer was awigen.
  <a href="2017.html#hangprinter_project_39">Read more...</a>
</p>
<br /><br /><br />
</oldpost>

<oldpost id="hangprinter_project_38" heading="Hangprinter.org" date="2-4-2017">
<p>
  Check it out: <a href="http://hangprinter.org/">hangprinter.org</a>!
  Big thanks to <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/piyush-dharnidharka-87083546/">Piyush Dharnidharka</a> for taking the initiative and building the page.
  <a href="2017.html#hangprinter_project_38">Read more...</a>
</p>
<br /><br /><br />
</oldpost>

<oldpost id="hangprinter_project_37" heading="Push Fit Sandwich" date="27-3-2017">
<p>
  In <a href="http://forums.reprap.org/read.php?1,738858,758625#msg-758625">this</a> forum post,
  NOVAprint confirmed what I had suspected was a weakness in the sandwich design.
  A gap might open between the snelle and the sandwich gear, so that line wraps around the center cylinder.
  I never really liked the super-short screws in the sandwich either, so I've designed a push fit solution:
  <a href="2017.html#hangprinter_project_37">Read more...</a>
</p>
<br /><br /><br />
</oldpost>

<oldpost id="hangprinter_project_36" heading="Sstruder v2 and Helsingborg" date="27-3-2017">
<p>
  I got the chance to test the improved extruder design recently. It worked better than the previous Sstruder, so stls were pushed to the repo today.
  <a href="2017.html#hangprinter_project_36">Read more...</a>
</p>
<br /><br /><br />
</oldpost>

<oldpost id="hangprinter_project_35" heading="Tweets" date="7-3-2017">
<p>
  I posted a few Tweets recently. Reposting them here now.
  <a href="2017.html#hangprinter_project_35">Read more...</a>
</p>
<br /><br /><br />
</oldpost>

<oldpost id="hangprinter_project_34" heading="The Tilt Problem" date="26-2-2017">
<p>
  Hello Reprappers and Hangprinterers!
  The Babel print gives a lot of lessons, so there's a lot of posts this week.
  Ca 1.5 m above ground and with 20 m of line on the D-spool, I've noticed a previously undocumented problem.
  <a href="2017.html#hangprinter_project_34">Read more...</a>
</p>
<br /><br /><br />
</oldpost>

<oldpost id="hangprinter_project_33" heading="Changed Anchor Points Mid Print" date="24-2-2017">
<p>
  I managed to sneak up the anchor points yesterday.
  The secret trick is to pause and move one anchor point at a time.
  <a href="2017.html#hangprinter_project_33">Read more...</a>
</p>
<br /><br /><br />
</oldpost>

<oldpost id="hangprinter_project_32" heading="Slowly but Surely" date="23-2-2017">
<p>
  920 first millemeters of a Babel Tower in a staircase.
  <a href="2017.html#hangprinter_project_32">Read more...</a>
</p>
<br /><br /><br />
</oldpost>

<oldpost id="hangprinter_project_31" heading="Community at Embryo Stage" date="20-2-2017">
<p>
  It seems like some collaboration and maybe even a little community is gathering around the Hangprinter Project.
  Right now, there are 5-6 builders out there wrapping their heads around the source files, assembly process and calibration.
  <a href="2017.html#hangprinter_project_31">Read more...</a>
</p>
<br /><br /><br />
</oldpost>

<oldpost id="hangprinter_project_30" heading="D-Wobble Debugged" date="2-2-2017">
<p>
  Those who have zoomed in on my Hangprints after I added the worm drive will have noticed a periodic error.
  <a href="2017.html#hangprinter_project_30">Read more...</a>
</p>
<br /><br /><br />
</oldpost>

<oldpost id="hangprinter_project_29" heading="Experimental Line Buildup Compensation Feature" date="27-1-2017">
<p>
  I've conducted a few experiments recently,
    and I think I've arrived at a usable implementation of the line buildup compensation that I described in
  <a href="2016.html#hangprinter_project_26">an earlier blog post</a>.
  In this post, I'll try to go a bit more in detail.
  <a href="2017.html#hangprinter_project_29">Read more...</a>
</p>
<br /><br /><br />
</oldpost>

<oldpost id="hangprinter_project_28" heading="Hangprinter Presentation Video and Campaign" date="15-1-2017">
<p>
  I've been helped by some friends to make a <a href="https://salt.bountysource.com/teams/hangprinter">campaign</a>.
  It has a presentation video and a logo and a picture of me and everything!
  <a href="2017.html#hangprinter_project_28">Read more...</a>
</p>
<br /><br /><br />
</oldpost>

<hr />
<h3>2016</h3>
<hr />
<br /><br /><br />

<oldpost id="hangprinter_project_27" heading="Compensation May Allow Bigger Prints" date="14-12-2016">
<p>
  The line compensation code may increase print volume noticeably.
  During testing, it has allowed Hangprinter version 2 to go places
  where version 1 surely would have over-tightened lines and skipped steps.
  <a href="2016.html#hangprinter_project_27">Read more...</a>
</p>
<br /><br /><br />
</oldpost>

<oldpost id="hangprinter_project_26" heading="Compensating Line Buildup on Spools" date="11-12-2016">
<p>
  I've added to Hangprinter-Marlins some code that
  compensates for line buildup on the spools.
  Without it, I found that error in steps/mm grew to several percent
  as print dimensions grew close to 1 m.
  The problem was particularly noticeable on the D-axis since it has three doubled lines,
  so moving 1 mm in the D-direction puts 6 mm of line on the D-spool.
  <a href="2016.html#hangprinter_project_26">Read more...</a>
</p>
<br /><br /><br />
</oldpost>

<oldpost id="hangprinter_project_25" heading="The Worm Drive Works" date="8-12-2016">
<p>
  Just tested the worm drive.
  I was so happy to see it work that I made a little video.
  <a href="2016.html#hangprinter_project_25">Read more...</a>
</p>
<br /><br /><br />
</oldpost>

<oldpost id="hangprinter_project_24" heading="Adjustable D Line Lengths and New Look" date="26-11-2016">
<p>
  Just made the D-line lengths easier to adjust independently.
  This is useful to get Hangprinter's corners in level with bed.
  Newest changes are at a
  <a href="https://github.com/tobbelobb/hangprinter/tree/adjustable_d_lines_and_new_look">new branch in the repo</a>.
  <a href="2016.html#hangprinter_project_24">Read more...</a>
</p>
<br /><br /><br />
</oldpost>

<oldpost id="hangprinter_project_23" heading="Worm Drive on D-axis" date="18-11-2016">
<p>
  The best part is that the worm is pure parametrized OpenSCAD and renders nicely.
  <a href="2016.html#hangprinter_project_23">Read more...</a>
</p>
<br /><br /><br />
</oldpost>

<oldpost id="hangprinter_project_22" heading="Another Stop Motion Video" date="5-11-2016">
<p>
  Hangprinting 0.9 m high twisted P at Teknisk Museum's 3D-printerfestival.
  Note: this text was edited on 7-11-2016.
  <a href="2016.html#hangprinter_project_22">Read more...</a>
</p>
<br /><br /><br />
</oldpost>

<oldpost id="hangprinter_project_21" heading="Hangprinter Calibration Manual v0.1" date="3-11-2016">
<p>
  This post will make it easier to calibrate Clerck by avoiding the need for measurements like this:
  <a href="2016.html#hangprinter_project_21">Read more...</a>
</p>
<br /><br /><br />
</oldpost>

<oldpost id="oslo_skaperfestival_2016" heading="Oslo Skaperfestival 2016" date="25-10-2016">
<p>
  Clerck was demonstrated in public for the first time this weekend!
  <a href="2016.html#oslo_skaperfestival_2016">Read more...</a>
</p>
<br /><br /><br />
</oldpost>

<oldpost id="hangprinter_project_20" heading="Homing the Hangprinter Without Adding Hardware" date="23-9-2016">
<p>
  I've thought some more about Hangprinter recently, since I'm going to demonstrate it on the
  <a href="https://www.facebook.com/events/1052788231502429/">3d printer festival</a>
  arranged by the Norwegian Museum of Science and Technology in Oslo.
  I've only ever mounted and calibrated Hangprinter once before,
    so getting the manual homing to work fast enough worries me a bit.
  I don't have the time to implement the proposed
  <a href="http://www.appropedia.org/Clerck,_a_RepRap_3D_printer_hanging_from_the_ceiling#Home_position">accelerometer dependent homing procedure</a>
  before the festival.
  <a href="2016.html#hangprinter_project_20">Read more...</a>
</p>
<br /><br /><br />
</oldpost>

<oldpost id="VSE_1" heading="Yet Another Very Simple Extruder Design" date="21-9-2016">
<p>
  I've thought about a second generation Hangprinter lately, including the extruder.
  My current favourite re-design uses two motors running synchronously.
  <a href="2016.html#VSE_1">Read more...</a>
</p>
<br /><br /><br />
</oldpost>

<oldpost id="masters_2" heading="Why Optimize Chaotic Production?" date="10-9-2016">
<p>
  RepRappers have noticed me that basing the story line of my
    <a href="http://opensourceecology.org/wiki/File:Thesis.pdf">my Master's thesis</a>
  on productivity numbers doesn't resonate with them.
  This tickled me to think about and formulate why I do what I do, hence this post.
  <a href="2016.html#masters_2">Read more...</a>
</p>
<br /><br /><br />
</oldpost>

<oldpost id="portable_gcode_1" heading="Portable Gcode and Short Status" date="5-9-2016">
<p>
  Today I asked a <a href="http://forums.reprap.org/read.php?1,705311">question on reprap forums</a> that has puzzled me for a long time.
  Why don't we share gcode instead of 3d models?
  The technical obstacles are small and it would be an obvious optimization of chaotic production.
  See <a href="http://forums.reprap.org/read.php?1,705311">the forum post</a> for details.
  Hoping for an interesting discussion there.
  <a href="2016.html#portable_gcode_1">Read more...</a>
</p>
<br /><br /><br />
</oldpost>

<oldpost id="masters_1" heading="Optimize Chaotic Production" date="29-6-2016">
<p>
  I presented my Master's recently, with a story line that was very RepRap centric.
  I'd like to re-present and develop my thoughts with some colors here.
  Be warned that this is a post about <i>why</i> I RepRap, not <i>how</i> I RepRap.
  <a href="2016.html#masters_1">Read more...</a>
</p>
<br /><br /><br />
</oldpost>

<oldpost id="hangprinter_project_19" heading="Update and Clerck Build Instructions" date="8-2-2016">
<p>
  I've been working on Open Source Ecology 3D printer workshops (see my <a href="http://opensourceecology.org/wiki/Tobben_Log">work log</a> for exactly what I've been up to)
  the past month, and will continue to work on that until mid summer.
  <a href="2016.html#hangprinter_project_19">Read more...</a>
</p>
<br /><br /><br />
</oldpost>
</posts>
