<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="blogtemplate.xsl"?>
<posts year="2020">
  <post id="hangprinter_project_63" heading="Introducing Line Collision Detector" date="22-7-2020">
    <p>
      I got asked again recently, about the Hangprinter print volume.
      How big is it really?
      The short answer is that there is no well defined print volume.
      The long answer is complicated.
    </p>
    <h3>The Long Answer</h3>
    <p>
      First, lets split the question into two parts:
      <ul>
        <li>Where can we reach?</li>
        <li>What can we print?</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <h3>The Reachable Volume</h3>
	  <figure>
	  	<a href="./bilder/ReachableVolume.png">
	  		<img src="./bilder/ReachableVolume_liten.png" alt="" width="500" height="444"/>
	  	</a>
	  	<figcaption>
	  	</figcaption>
	  </figure>
    <p>
      The Hangprinter's effector is fully constrained when moving within the tetrahedron spanned up by its four anchors.
      An evil AI driven firmware could theoretically use the motors to toss the effector out of this envelope, but let's ignore that possibility
      and call the anchor-spanned tetrahedron <i>the reachable volume</i>.
    </p>
    <p>
      I reality, we won't be able to print close to the walls of the reachable volume, since gravity will make
      the effector sag inwards.
      So <i>the usable volume</i> is a few percent smaller than the reachable volume.
      Exactly how much sag to expect could be calculated from the weight of the effector and the maximum static force of the motors,
      but let's save those calculations for another blog post.
    </p>
	  <figure>
	  	<a href="./bilder/hp_volume.png">
	  		<img src="./bilder/hp_volume_liten.png" alt="" width="500" height="293"/>
	  	</a>
	  	<figcaption>
        Fred Hedenberg made this nice and correct rendering of the usable print volume of a particular Hangprinter.
	  	</figcaption>
	  </figure>
    <p>
      This is where I wish we could end the analysis and say "print volume = tetrahedron minus sag".
      But alas.
      We cannot fill up the whole usable volume with tetrahedron-shaped benchy fractals.
      At least not in a single big print.
    </p>
    <h3>So, For Any Particular 3d-model: Can we print it?</h3>
    <p>
      With Hangprinter we also have to consider the risk that lines might collide with the half-finished print.
      Every tad of extruded material is a potential obstacle that the Hangprinter's every subsequent move must avoid.
    </p>
    <p>
      Consider the following render to get some intuition about what a line collision is and how it occurs:
    </p>
	  <figure>
	  	<a href="./bilder/cone_shapes.jpg">
	  		<img src="./bilder/cone_shapes_liten.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="344"/>
	  	</a>
	  	<figcaption>
        The Hangprinter's effector is attached to the ground with 6 different lines.
        For each layer, each line will move within a "cone shape". The top of the cone shape is a convex hull of the current top layer.
	  	</figcaption>
	  </figure>
    <p>
      And as evidence that these collisions are a real world problem, consider this failed spiral vase that I printed at an event:
    </p>
	  <figure>
	  	<a href="./bilder/line-collision.png">
	  		<img src="./bilder/line-collision_liten.png" alt="" width="500" height="719"/>
	  	</a>
	  	<figcaption>
        This print continued and survived the line collision (with a 1 cm deep artifact) because it was a smooth spiral vase.
        The more common case is that lines snap, prints break loose, big disasters of various kinds.
	  	</figcaption>
	  </figure>
    <p>
      Actually, the answer to the question "is this object printable in my Hangprinter?", depends on
      how your object is rotated,
      where it's placed on the build plate,
      and in which order you put down the material!
      Lots of stuff to think about. (Uuugh...)
    </p>
    <p>
      I'm just teasing you with all these horrible facts.
      There now exists a program that lets you check if you will get a line collision or not.
      It's called
      <a href="https://gitlab.com/hangprinter/line-collision-detector">line-collision-detector</a>.
    </p>

  </post>
</posts>
