<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="blogtemplate.xsl"?>
<posts year="or maybe not. Super Secret.">
  <post id="super_secret_1" heading="Project Overhanger" date="4-11-2021">
    <p>
      So I've been thinking recently, about making a kit.
      Hangprinter v4 is now more or less done.
      It's not polished, but I've seen what it can do.
      Next version ideas keep creeping up on me.
    </p>
    <p>
      I imagine a new machine that's not a Hangprinter.
      It's different from Hangprinter because
      it disregards self-replication, generous licensing, decentralization,
      ideology, and history.
      It makes me feel like a heretic. But it also makes me feel free.
      All it wants is to be loved by the imperfect and uneducated strangers who will be its users.
    </p>
    <p>
      Hangprinter wanted to educate people.
      Overhanger wants to make people pay for a user experience.
    </p>
    <p>
      This post tries to stitch together ideas and experiences from the Hangprinter Project
      that would guide the Overhanger Project.
    </p>
    <h3>Overhanger Should Be</h3>
    <p>
      a machine that
      <ol>
        <li>is enjoyable to use.</li>
        <li>I enjoy using myself.</li>
        <li>runs quietly.</li>
        <li>let's me leave the room.</li>
        <li>is easily stowed away after use, leaving the room cleared.</li>
        <li>requires no hand measurements by the user. Basically commissions itself.</li>
        <li>plug and play compatible with commercially available tool heads.</li>
        <li>multi-unit.</li>
        <li>serves the unserved.</li>
        <li>is driven by computer vision.</li>
      </ol>
    </p>
    <p>
      Points 1 through 7 are already fulfilled by HP4, although I'm sure we would like to polish some of them a bit more.
    </p>
    <p>
      When it's switched on, HP4 doesn't make a sound.
      Lines have never fallen off bearings in between uses, like earlier HP's lines did.
    </p>
    <p>
      While printing, HP4 is still completely quiet.
      There's no risk that lines will fall off during print.
      Wearing down it's thick lines will take an eternity.
      I worry a lot less when I leave the room with HP4 running,
      compared to how I felt about leaving earlier Hangprinters running.
    </p>
    <p>
      The automatic calibration just worked on the first try.
    </p>
    <p>
      The spool that rewinds the electric cables fixed a stowing issue that earlier Hangprinters had.
      Whenever I stowed away earlier Hangprinters up to the ceiling, there would still be a cable loop hanging down.
      The HP4 keeps its cables closer to the ceiling, freeing up the space below more easily.
    </p>
    <p>
      Here follows elaborations on the things that Overhanger should become, that HP4 isn't already.
    </p>
    <h4>8. Multi-Unit</h4>
    <p>
      The HP0, HP1, and HP2 were all single-unit. All the electronics was concentrated in one unit; the mover.
    </p>
    <p>
      The HP3 and HP4 are dual-unit. Their electronics are split between the ceiling unit and the mover.
    </p>
    <p>
      The Overhanger should have a motor and some electronics at every anchor, and some on the mover.
      I call this hardware layout multi-unit.
    </p>
    <p>
      It gives shorter lines, less flex, and less friction compared to dual unit.
      It also gives less lines suspended through the air compared to dual-unit.
      And it reduces the risk of falling of a ladder while fiddling with electronics.
    </p>
    <p>
      Compared to single-unit it gives a simpler, lighter mover.
    </p>
    <h4>9. Serves the Unserved</h4>
    <p>
      Those already invested in ball screws are out of our reach.
      We must find others, who don't have frames already ingrained in their brains.
    </p>
    <p>
      These other people aren't used to doing any kind of manufacturing.
      They typically dislike computers, plastics, and risk.
      They like nature, hand-made things, feelings, and art.
      They will give their machine a name, assign it a personality, decorate it, and never touch it with a screwdriver unless they have to.
      They will want to stand on the mover and be floated around for fun, unless there's a sticker there that says "don't stand on it".
    </p>
    <p>
      However, they don't really want a machine at all.
      This is why Overhanger must look very minimalistic, and not make a sound.
    </p>
    <p>
      They will only buy it because they want the crazy shapes it enables.
      They want anything that can recycle plastic waste into Gaudi-shaped bookshelves and chairs.
      They want personal ceramic cups and plates.
      Any weird shape with a story behind it.
    </p>
    <p>
      Our users would be like <a href="https://thenewraw.org/">these people</a> and <a href="https://dirkvanderkooij.com/">this guy</a>.
      Despite automation of the process being the thing they're achieving,
      they will still want to feel like they deserve to hand sign their works,
      like <a href="https://oliviervanherpt.com/white-textured-vase/">this guy</a>.
    </p>
    <p>
      Let's stop here and comment on the fact that all the people I've linked to look like exceptions.
      They all seem to work at, or be former students of, wealthy design institutions.
      How representative are they?
      I think their high level preferences and feelings for manufacturing are representative for the people we want to reach.
      I think the group who care about shape and color outnumbers the current 3d printer community by a factor of at least 10x, maybe 100x.
    </p>
    <p>
      Side note on group size:
      In the building where I have my 3d printing office, there are ceramics courses every day, with 20 participants.
      That's 100 people per week who pay for the privilege to create with clay and color in a big group.
      I know about 3 other similar places in Gothenburg where I live.
      So ~400 people per week, out of ~500k inhabitants, do this clay thing in any given week.
    </p>
    <p>
      There are no 3d-printing courses at all in all of Gothenburg.
    </p>
    <p>
      I think for many, it would be a net positive if the machines sometimes stopped and asked for things, like:
      <ul>
        <li>Please change the pen for a yellow one.</li>
        <li>Please refill with white clay and colourant.</li>
        <li>Please insert reinforcement bar in the printed pocket.</li>
        <li>Please shape the extruded clay blob into a little flower and press resume.</li>
      </ul>
      The machine asking for favours would make them feel more needed and less alienated.
    </p>
    <p>
      And they want to post process the prints, or alternatively make a big point about not doing it.
      There are three talking points that dominate their thoughts when it comes to 3d printing:
      <ol>
        <li>The material, </li>
        <li>the layer lines, </li>
        <li>and the shape.</li>
      </ol>
      After too many years in 3d printing, I'm a little envious about how high up "shape" is on their list.
    </p>
    <p>
      See for example <a href="https://youtu.be/Mhk1r5lyzKI">here</a> for how they feel about their own craftsmanship
      in the  post processing step (and how they must contact tech support to learn that printing along a square's diagonal is possible).
      Or <a href="https://3dprint.com/282262/3d-printed-furniture-and-design-the-time-is-now/">here</a> for another overview of their style of thought.
    </p>
    <p>
      Any human interaction and post processing makes the products feel more hand made.
      Like bags of baking mix ask them to add egg and milk, although that could have been part of the powder all along.
      It just feels better for some to do part of the work by hand.
    </p>
    <p>
      These users have up until now paid up for robot arms, and every project has been a one-off.
      For a state of the art offering towards this group, see <a href="https://www.3dwasp.com/en/3d-printed-furniture-when-art-meet-additive-manufacturing/">this ad for a $40,000 machine</a>.
    </p>
    <p>
      On second thought, we shouldn't call it Overhanger. We should call it what they want: SHAPES!.
    </p>
    <p>
      I was one of these lively unserved people.
      Then I reduced my liveliness until I was an engineer.
      It's easy to forget why I wanted Hangprinter in the first place.
      But this is it, I believe.
    </p>
    <h4>10. Is Driven By Computer Vision</h4>
    <p>
      In some ways this is a continuation of an earlier blog post called <a href="../2020/#hangprinter_project_68">On Demand Precision</a>.
    </p>
    <p>
      Computer vision might sound like an optional luxury add-on that we could do without.
      For most concrete use cases of the computer vision system, there exist other potential solutions
      that rely on
      <ul>
        <li>line tension data,</li>
        <li>line length measurements,</li>
        <li>bed proximity sensors,</li>
        <li>maybe some accelerometer data,</li>
        <li>maybe some basic encoder tricks,</li>
        <li>or increasingly complicated physics models based on a growing list of assumptions.</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <p>
      We should do all those things when we have time.
      But we should also do computer vision.
      And we should do computer vision first because it aids the development of all the others.
      The others don't aid the computer vision.
    </p>
    <p>
      Some use cases include
      <ul>
        <li>Automated homing</li>
        <li>Verification during print that the print head is exactly where it's supposed to be</li>
        <li>Safety feature: if anything except the effector is moving inside the print volume, pause the print, raise an alarm. This will save pets.</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <p>
      But outside of specific use cases:
      The computer vision system is great because it introduces redundancy.
      It measures where the print head is, with very few assumptions.
      Even if all lines snapped, even if CAN goes down.
      It's cheap, intuitive, and already available.
    </p>
    <p>
      Image data makes a wide range of situations recoverable, who wouldn't otherwise be.
      <ul>
        <li>An encoder slips,</li>
        <li>there's a power outage,</li>
        <li>a gear is loose on a motor shaft,</li>
        <li>an old bearing destroys line tension data,</li>
        <li>the print head crashes into something during print and gets a tilted mover after that,</li>
        <li>the print is paused during night because a landlord doesn't trust machine to not spontaneously catch fire. One of the lines stretches, and the whole hose warpes a bit during the pause.</li>
      </ul>
      To recover the last point, there must be fixated patterns on the floor/print bed to calibrate camera position against.
    </p>
    <p>
      We can't really get ahead of the very long tail of improbable failures.
      But we can automatically compensate, or in the worst case pause print automatically, and remain recoverable after any problem.
      If we introduce measurement redundancy.
    </p>
    <p>
      I'm aware that machinists are generally sceptical to the computer vision idea because so many had it before, and failed at implementing it well enough.
      The same is true for cable driven robotics in general.
      They are conservative for good reason, and it's very hard to prove them wrong.
      But that's what SHAPES! will be trying to do.
    </p>
  </post>
</posts>
