<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="blogtemplate.xsl"?>
<posts year="2021">
  <post id="super_secret_1" heading="Project Total Overhang" date="4-11-2021">
    <p>
      So I've been thinking recently, about making a kit.
      Hangprinter v4 is now more or less done.
      I've seen what it can do.
      Next version ideas keep creeping up on me.
    </p>
    <p>
      Let's call the new thing the Overhang. And the project is the Project Total Overhang.
    </p>
    <p>
      This post tries to stitch together ideas and experiences that will drive my future Hangprinter work, whether it's Hangprinter v5 or the Overhang.
    </p>
    <h3>I Would Want to Make</h3>
    <p>
      a machine that
      <ol>
        <li>is enjoyable to use.</li>
        <li>I enjoy using myself.</li>
        <li>runs quietly.</li>
        <li>let's me leave the room.</li>
        <li>is easily stoved away after use, leaving the room cleared.</li>
        <li>requires no hand measurements by the user. Basically comissions itself.</li>
        <li>plug and play compatible with commercially available tool heads.</li>
        <li>serves the unserved.</li>
        <li>is driven by computer vision.</li>
        <li>beats conventional CNC machinery on every single metric.</li>
      </ol>
    </p>
    <p>
      Points 1 through 7 are already fulfilled by HP4, although I'm sure we would like to polish some of them a bit more.
    </p>
    <h4>Serves the Unserved</h4>
    <p>
      Those already invested in ballscrews are out of our reach.
      They are right to be very skeptic about line driven precision machinery.
      We must find others, who don't have frames already ingrained in their brains.
    </p>
    <p>
      These other people aren't used to doing any kind of manufacturing.
      They must be tempted into doing it.
      The Overhang must be made unresistable to them in many more ways than a typical CNC machine usually is.
      It must look good, and sound good (be quiet).
      It must help them brag by for example doing little tricks with tennis balls, and posting its own updates on social media when a print is finished.
      It must not smell bad, like molten plastic does.
    </p>

    <h4>Is Driven By Computer Vision</h4>
    <p>
      In some ways this is a continuation of an earlier blog post called <a href="../2020/#hangprinter_project_68">On Demand Precision</a>.
    </p>
    <p>
      Computer vision might sound like an optional luxury add-on that we could do without.
      For most concrete use cases of the computer vision system, there exist other potential solutions
      that rely on
      <ul>
        <li>line tension data,</li>
        <li>line lenght measurements,</li>
        <li>bed proximity sensors,</li>
        <li>maybe some accelerometer data,</li>
        <li>maybe some basic encoder tricks,</li>
        <li>or increasingly complicated physics models based on a growing heap of assumptions.</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <p>
      We should do all those things when we have time.
      But we should also do computer vision.
      And we should do computer vision first because it aids the development of all the others.
      The others don't aid the computer vision.
    </p>
    <p>
      Some use cases include
      <ul>
        <li>Automated homing</li>
        <li>Verification durint print that the print head is exactly where it's supposed to be</li>
        <li>Safety feature: if anything except the effector is moving inside the print volume, pause the print, raise an alarm. This will save many prints, but also cats and dogs.</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <p>
      But forget the use cases.
      The computer vision system is superior to all the other measurement solutions because it covers every imaginable
      use case and introduces redundancy.
      It measures exactly the thing we want to know, which is "Where is the print head right now?", instead of measuring a proxy to that.
      It's cheap, and
      knowing the exact position at all times, even if all lines snapped and all motors are offline, is simply unbeatable value.
    </p>
    <p>
      Such data makes a wide range of situations recoverable, who is almost impossible to recover otherwise.
      <ul>
        <li>An encoder slips,</li>
        <li>there's a power outage,</li>
        <li>a gear is loose on a motor shaft,</li>
        <li>an old bearing destroys line tension data,</li>
        <li>the print head crashes into something during print and gets a tilted mover after that,</li>
        <li>a print was paused during night because a landlord didn't trust machine to not catch fire, and one of the lines stretched, or the whole hose warped, by 0.1 mm during that pause.</li>
      </ul>
      Stuff like that happens a lot, it happens all the time. Maybe 90% of large prints have some kind of incident that leaves a visible artifact on the print.
      Most large prints have many.
    </p>
    <p>
      We don't want to predict and prevent every single thing that could happen.
      Instead we want to automatically pause at the right time, and be perfectly recoverable afterwards, regardless of what the problem might have been.
    </p>
    <p>
      I'm aware that machinists are generally sceptical to the computer vision idea because so many had it before, and failed at implementing it well enough.
      The same is true for cable driven robotics in general.
      When time resources get tight, and there is no cheap programmer around, machinists always revert back to century old trusted methods.
      And the old methods serve them well.
      Mechanical simplicity is not easy to beat with digital measurement and compensation.
      But that's what we will be trying to do.
      So we should bring out the large cannons, and make as few assumptions as we can.
    </p>
    <h4>Beats Conventional CNC Machinery on Every Single Metric</h4>
    <p>
      We want to wipe the floor with framed machines by exceeding their
      <ul>
        <li>realiability,</li>
        <li>precision and accuracy,</li>
        <li>speed,</li>
      </ul>
      while reducing
      <ul>
        <li>cost of investment,</li>
        <li>cost of transportation,</li>
        <li>cost of installation and comissioning,</li>
        <li>cost of personel training,</li>
        <li>cost of daily usage,</li>
        <li>cost of storage</li>
      </ul>
      to less than 10% of similar-volume framed machines.
    </p>
    <p>
      Among the six types of cost, the cost of storage is by far the biggest, most important, and most overlooked.
      Typical CNC users never imagined being able to escape the cost of having to give up floor space in their shop for a large CNC machine.
    </p>
    <p>
      The Overhang asks users to not box in the floor layouts of their workshops.
      Changing workshop floor layouts usually takes a generation or more.
      People get very used to the layouts of the spaces they inhabit.
    </p>
  </post>
</posts>
