<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="blogtemplate.xsl"?>
<posts year="2022">
  <post id="rust_1" heading="Brackets in Rust" date="21-8-2022">
    <p>
      New Rust programmers notice that
      Rust uses angle brackets (or chevrons) like this &lt; and this&gt; a lot.
      When should they be used and when can they be omitted?
    </p>
    <h3>Let's Start With Rounded Brackets First</h3>
    <p>
      The round brackets (or parentheses) are more familiar to any old programmer.
      I'll compare Rust to C and Common Lisp, just to have something very old to reference back to.
    </p>
    <p>
      Parenthesis mean "compute this now" in almost all programming languages.
      Zero or more bound variables and/or literal values should compute into zero or more return values.
    </p>
    <p>
      In Common Lisp, a <code>(</code> always means "thing starts" and <code>)</code> means "thing ends".
      In other languages, things may start before the <code>(</code>.
      C does some of both, with for example function calls and grouping of expressions:
    </p>
    <p>
      <ul>
        <li><code>f(x)</code></li>
        <li><code>(1 + 2 + 3)</code></li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <p>
      The second example works the same in Rust as in C.
      Functions are more complicated.
      Let's look at C's function declaration first:
    </p>
    <p>
      <code>out_type f(in_type);</code>
    </p>
    <p>
      The pre-defined types <code>in_type</code> and <code>out_type</code> describe inputs and outputs of the function <code>f</code>.
      Here, the parentheses don't mean "compute this now".
      Instead it means "prepare for computation request like this one later".
    </p>
    <p>
    </p>
    <p>
      The closest equivalent in ideomatic compileable Rust code would be:
    </p>
    <p>
      <code>trait A { fn f(_: in_type) -> out_type; }</code>
    </p>
    <p>
      In Rust, you can't declare a free function without a body.
      The simplest possible free function would have an empty body and an unspecified return type:
    </p>
    <p>
      <code>fn f(_: in_type) {}</code>
    </p>
    <p>
      The <code>_</code> means "unused variable", like in Erlang and many pattern matching languages.
      The Common Lisp, you could declare without implementation like in C:
    </p>
    <p>
      <code>(declaim (ftype (function (in_type)) f))</code>
    </p>
    <p>
      Or you can do both declaration and implementation at once like in Rust:
    </p>
    <p>
      <code>(defun f (_) (declare (ignore _) (in_type _)))</code>
    </p>
    <p>
      In a real Lisp project who wanted types, one would probably use a library like <a href="https://github.com/lisp-maintainers/defstar">defstar</a> to be able to write:
    </p>
    <p>
      <code>(defun* f ((_ in_type)))</code>
    </p>
    <p>
      An unspecified return type in Rust defaults to <code>()</code>, which is a primitive type that has only one value that is also called <code>()</code>.
      Both the type and the value are often referred to as the unit.
      It's empty and means "compute nothing" or "this is nothing", similar to <code>void</code> in C, or indeed equivalent to <code>()</code> in Common Lisp.
      The empty body also behaves like in Common Lisp, it defaults to returning <code>()</code>.
    </p>
    <p>
      An additional meaning of parentheses in Rust. Great. Let's write Rust's defaults out explicitly so we have seen them at least once:
    </p>
    <p>
      <code>fn f(_: in_type) -> () { () }</code>
    </p>
    <!--p>
      We'll sometimes skip over implementation bodies and only write Rust's function signatures patterns:
    </p>
    <p>
      <code>fn f(_: in_type) -> out_type </code>
    </p-->
    <p>
      Read it like

      <table style="text-align: right; border-spacing: 0px; margin-left: 10px;; margin-right: 10px;">
        <tbody>
          <tr><td style="width: 10%"><code>fn f( </code></td><td>"This is a function called f, it has the following parameters..."</td></tr>
          <tr><td style="width: 10%"><code>_ </code></td><td> "... an unnamed one..."</td></tr>
          <tr><td style="width: 10%"><code>:  </code></td><td> "... here follows a description of the parameter..."</td></tr>
          <tr><td style="width: 10%"><code>in_type </code></td><td> "... the name of the parameter's type..."</td></tr>
          <tr><td style="width: 10%"><code>) </code></td><td> "... end of parameter list..."</td></tr>
          <tr><td style="width: 10%"><code> ->  </code></td><td> "... here follows a description of the function's output"</td></tr>
          <tr><td style="width: 10%"><code>in_type </code></td><td> "... the name of the function's return type."</td></tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </p>
    <h3>Rust's Angle Brackets are for Generic Data Types</h3>
    <p>
      Let's look at a slightly more complicated Rust function:
    </p>
    <p>
      <code>fn f&lt;InType&gt;(_: InType) {}</code>
    </p>
    <p>
      This looks like what we have seen before, except <code>InType</code> is now mentioned inside angle brackets (chevrons),
      right before the parenthesis that starts the parameter list.
      In this case the angle brackets modifies the meaning of <code>InType</code> to mean, not the name of a particular type,
      but a variable (generic type) that will resolve to zero or more concrete types, and a function will be generated for each type,
      when the function is compiled.
      So <code>f</code> is here not one function, but a family of functions who only differ in what type they use as their <code>InType</code>.
    </p>
    <p>
      C doesn't generate families of functions. C could use typecasting to achieve something vaguely similar with a single function,
      but it wouldn't be the same.
    </p>
    <p>
      The Common Lisp equivalent comes more naturally:
    </p>
    <p>
      <code>(defun f (_) (declare (ignore _)))</code>
    </p>
    <p>
      Common Lisp will always detect automatically which one among the family of functions called <code>f</code> that should be applied.
      You call it like: <code>(f 1)</code>
      Rust can also auto detect in this trivial case, so you can call <code>f</code> as if it was a single function: <code>f(1)</code>
    </p>
    <p>
      However, Rust has some more advanced features that forces you to specify which <code>f</code> you want. Take a look at this:
    </p>
    <p>
      <code>fn f&lt;T: Default&gt;() -> T { T::default() }</code>
    </p>
    <p>
      Read it like

      <table style="text-align: right; border-spacing: 0px; margin-left: 10px; margin-right: 10px;">
        <tbody>
          <tr><td style="width: 21%"><code>fn f&lt;</code></td><td>"A family of functions <code>f</code>, who differ by ..."</td></tr>
          <tr><td style="width: 21%"><code>T</code></td><td> "... a type variable, <code>T</code>, which represents any type..."</td></tr>
          <tr><td style="width: 21%"><code>: </code></td><td> "... that fulfills..."</td></tr>
          <tr><td style="width: 21%"><code>Default</code></td><td> "... a trait called <code>Default</code>."</td></tr>
          <tr><td style="width: 21%"><code>&gt;</code></td><td> "Start defining functions <code>f</code>, with type variable(s) in scope."</td></tr>
          <tr><td style="width: 21%"><code>() -> T { </code></td><td> "Empty parameter list. <code>T</code> used as return type."</td></tr>
          <tr><td style="width: 21%"><code>T::default()</code></td><td> "Call into <code>T</code>'s associated <code>default()</code> function."</td></tr>
          <tr><td style="width: 21%"><code>}</code></td><td> "End of body."</td></tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </p>
    <p>
      When we call into one of these functions, Rust can't always infer which <code>f</code> we meant.
      Placing a function call <code>f()</code> on a line of code without further type information won't be valid Rust and won't compile.
      Rust will not take a guess on your behalf.
    </p>
    <p>
      One way to provide the compiler with the type info it needs, is with Rust's second-ugliest syntax in my opinion, the <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/rust/comments/3fimgp/comment/ctozkd0/">turbofish</a>:
    </p>
    <p>
      <code>f::&lt;some_concrete_type&gt;();</code>
    </p>
    <p>
      The turbofish, <code>::&lt;&gt;</code>, lets you treat <code>f</code> like one function who just needs its type parameters and other parameters to be provided separately.
    </p>
    <p>
      Both grouping types by who implements a particular function, the <code>default</code> in the above example, and passing types to functions (families) are way beyond C's type system.
    </p>
    <p>
      But can Common Lisp still keep up?
      Like, can we somehow say:
    </p>
    <p>
      <code>(f 'fixnum)</code>
    </p>
    <p>
      ... and get back the default value of the concrete type called <code>fixnum</code>?
    </p>
    <p>
      The <code>'fixnum</code> above is really a symbol
      We can hack together something, like
    </p>
    <p>
      <code>(defgeneric default (x))<br />
        (defmethod default ((s (eql 'fixnum))) 42)<br />
        (defun f (s) (declare (symbol s)) (default s))<br />
        (f 'fixnum)<br />
          => 42
      </code>
    </p>
    <p>
      The <code>defgeneric</code> creates a dispatch table, and we're able to give <code>fixnum</code>
      it's own implementation.
      But, the <code>default</code> implementation is attached to a symbol, not to a type,
      and I can't get this to err at compile time without doing much more funky stuff.
    </p>
    <!--p>
      We could also do
    </p>
    <p>
      <code>(setf (get 'fixnum 'default) (lambda () 42))<br />
        (defun f (s) (declare (symbol s)) (funcall (get s 'default)))<br />
        (f 'fixnum)<br />
          => 42
      </code>
    </p-->
    <p>
      I guess we shaked off both C and Common Lisp already here.
      Rust's traits, and handling of types, over powers Common Lisp's built in
      type system in this comparison.
      Common Lisp is a programmable programming language, so we could simulate most of Rust's
      features in there.
      With common lisp macros, absolutely, we can do anything.
      But it would be hard, it would not be pretty, and I wouldn't want to do it.
    </p>
    <p>
      With that said, everything's not pretty in Rust either, even if it's
      directly available.
      But we'll take that another day.
    </p>
    <h3>Reading List</h3>
    <p>
      To really understand where to put colons and angle brackets in Rust code, I had to read these texts:
    </p>
    <p>
      <ul>
        <li><a href="https://techblog.tonsser.com/posts/what-is-rusts-turbofish">What is Rust's turbofish?</a></li>
        <li><a href="https://matematikaadit.github.io/posts/rust-turbofish.html">Where to put the turbofish</a></li>
        <li><a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/55113556/how-to-use-turbofish-operator-for-generic-trait-implementation">Fully Qualified Syntax Needed for Resolving Generic Traits</a></li>
        <li><a href="https://doc.rust-lang.org/book/ch19-03-advanced-traits.html#fully-qualified-syntax-for-disambiguation-calling-methods-with-the-same-name">Fully Qualified Syntax Docs</a></li>
      </ul>
    </p>
  </post>
</posts>
