<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="blogtemplate.xsl"?>
<posts year="2022">
  <post id="prior_art_1" heading="Prior Art Relevant to Patent US 11230032" date="2-2-2022">
    <p>
        The <a href="https://wayfinder.digital/fedinvent/patents-2022/details-patents-20220125.html#11230032_DOE">patent in question</a> was filed on Apr 13, 2018.
        We will refer to the patented contraption as SkyBAAM for short.
        We will present prior art relevant to SkyBAAM, all of which was unmentioned and unreferenced in the patent.
        The prior art we present will mostly have been published within context of the open source project called Hangprinter.
    </p>
    <p>
      The patent made only two references to Hangprinter:
      <ul>
        <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hangprinter">The Wikipedia Article</a></li>
        <li><a href="https://www.3ders.org/articles/20170308-frameless-hangprinter-reprap-turns-an-entire-room-into-a-3d-printer.html">An out of date article from 3ders.org</a></li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <p>
      Those two sources alone do not cover enough details to reveal how deeply similar SkyBAAM is to the pre-existing Hangprinter.
    </p>
    <h2>First Of All</h2>
    <p>
      The patent contains many ideas that have been explored, published, and then discontinued within the Hangprinter community.
    </p>
    <p>
      The Hangprinter prototype that was most visually similar to Fig 4 in the patent might be this
      early version 3 prototype, that was <a href="http://vitana.se/opr3d/tbear/2017#hangprinter_project_42">published and described in detail on April 4, 2017</a>.
    </p>
    <figure>
      <video width="500" controls="true">
        <source src="../2017/bilder/Freds_gopro.mp4" type="video/mp4"></source>
      </video>
      <figcaption>
        The video shows the first Hangprinter prototype that offloaded the motors and most of the electronics to one of the anchors.
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <figure>
      <a href="./media/Their_fig_4.png">
        <img src="./media/Their_fig_4_small.png" alt="" width="500" height="436"/>
      </a>
      <figcaption>
        Fig 4 from from the patent in question.
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>
      However, the similarities are not merely superficial.
      This text will show similarities on the conceptual level in the form of ideas that were formulated, and sometimes also implemented within the Hangprinter Project,
      before they were reiterated in the patent.
    </p>

    <h3>Let's Dive Into the Details</h3>
    <p>
      This writing will be long and detailed.
      The corpus of relevant prior art published publicly before April 13 2018 is vast,
      since the Hangprinter Project was already four years old at the time.
      This prior art includes (but is not limited to)
      <ul>
        <li><a href="https://torbjornludvigsen.com/blog/2018/#hangprinter_project_55">56 technical blog posts</a></li>
        <li>Ca 350 posts on Reprap forums<ul>
            <li><a href="https://reprap.org/forum/read.php?178,344022">thread 1</a></li>
            <li><a href="https://reprap.org/forum/read.php?1,738858">thread 2</a></li>
            <li><a href="https://reprap.org/forum/read.php?423,792937">thread 3</a></li>
          </ul>
        </li>
        <li><a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/hangprinter">A few hundred posts in the Facebook group</a></li>
        <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/results?search_query=Hangprinter&amp;sp=CAI%253D">Ca 25 relevant Youtube videos</a></li>
        <li><a href="https://vimeo.com/user23166500">37 videos published on Vimeo</a></li>
        <li><a href="https://twitter.com/tobbelobb">Ca 100 Tweets</a></li>
        <li><a href="https://hangprinter.org/newsletter/">13 Hangprinter Newsletters</a></li>
        <li>Wiki articles on <a href="https://www.appropedia.org/Clerck,_a_RepRap_3D_printer_hanging_from_the_ceiling">Appropedia</a>, and <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20180330041707/https://reprap.org/wiki/Hangprinter">Reprap Wiki</a>.</li>
        <!--li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hangprinter">Wikipedia</a></li-->
        <li><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20180405053344/http://hangprinter.org/">A hangprinter.org landing page</a></li>
        <li><a href="https://hangprinter.org/doc/v3/">Rich and visual documentation, created on April 10, 2018</a></li>
        <li><a href="https://github.com/tobbelobb/hangprinter">A public Github repo containing over 500 relevant commits and issues</a></li>
        <li>A number of news articles, including at
        <ul>
          <!--li><a href="https://www.3ders.org/articles/20170308-frameless-hangprinter-reprap-turns-an-entire-room-into-a-3d-printer.html">3ders.org</a></li-->
          <li><a href="https://hackaday.com/2017/03/20/hanging-3d-printer-uses-entire-room-as-print-bed/">hackaday.com</a></li>
          <li><a href="https://3dprintingindustry.com/news/interview-inventor-frameless-hangprinter-3d-printer-building-tower-babel-107749/">3dprintingindustry.com</a></li>
          <li><a href="https://www.seeker.com/open-source-prototype-turns-any-room-into-a-3d-printer-2313142390.html">seeker.com</a></li>
          <li><a href="https://hackaday.com/2017/12/16/hangprinter-build-videos/">hackaday.com again</a></li>
          <li><a href="https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2017/03/170308083723.htm">sciencedaily.com</a></li>
          <li><a href="https://www.fabbaloo.com/2017/03/the-hangprinter-a-frameless-3d-printer">fabbaloo.com</a></li>
          <li><a href="https://www.wired.com/beyond-the-beyond/2017/03/hangprinter-printer-just-sorta-hangs/">wired.com</a></li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <h2>Prior Art Published in the Repo</h2>
    <p>
      <a href="https://github.com/tobbelobb/hangprinter">The main Hangprinter repo</a> is the heart of the Hangprinter project.
    </p>
    <p>
      Hangprinter is developed following open source methodology.
      This means that all source files are published to the repo,
      freely for anyone to use,
      for any purpose, soon after they are created.
      They are also re-uploaded soon after any modification is made.
    </p>
    <p>
      The re-uploads do not overwrite old work.
      Instead, each change is registered in an elaborate version control system (git/Github),
      that presents the newest version to the user, as well as saving and catalouging every previous version in chronological order.
    </p>
    <p>
      The "source files" include, but are not limited to
      <ul>
        <li>CAD drawings</li>
        <li>Source code for programming the firmware of any microcontrollers involved</li>
        <li>Assembly and usage instructions</li>
        <li>A copyright license</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <p>
      The version controlled, and publicly available directory is called "the repo".
      It can be found <a href="https://github.com/tobbelobb/hangprinter">here</a>.
    </p>
    <h3>Was The Repo Publicly Available?</h3>
    <p>
      Anyone had access and usage rights to the repo on Apr 13, 2018.
    </p>
    <p>
      Information about how popular and well known the repo was on Apr 13, 2018 can be found by using <a href="http://archive.org">archive.org</a>, also known as Wayback Machine.
      It is service that stores and archives old web pages, so we can visit them again, and see exactly how they looked on given dates.
    </p>
    <p>
      This is how github.com/tobbelobb/hangprinter looked on Jun 26, 2017:
    </p>
    <figure>
      <a href="./media/Jun26_2017_Github.png">
        <img src="./media/Jun26_2017_Github_small.png" alt="" width="500" height="276"/>
      </a>
      <figcaption>
        Click the image for a larger version.
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>
      In the image we can see that the repo had 77 watchers, 248 stars, and 49 forks.
      This means that this was a popular repo at the time.
      The 49 forks means that at least 49 people have copied Hangprinter's source files
      to use as the basis for their own cable driven robot build.
    </p>
    <p>
      The license in the repo allows and encourages such copying.
      Hangprinter was the most popular and widely known basis for cable driven robot development in 2017 and 2018.
    </p>
    <h3>What Was In the Repo?</h3>
    <p>
      On Apr 13, 2018 the Hangprinter version 2 development had just been concluded (this happened on Feb 12, 2018).
      Work on Hangprinter version 3 had been going on since April 2017.
    </p>
    <p>
      The state of the art of version 2 in the repo on Apr 13, 2018 can be found <a href="https://github.com/tobbelobb/hangprinter/tree/c9295eceff474d44da9f7ad971b1a9f0303fea45">here</a>.
    </p>
    <p>
      The state of the art of version 3 in the repo on Apr 13, 2018 can be found <a href="https://github.com/tobbelobb/hangprinter/tree/3fa54dbe37858ce02146a2d9f31bb17343fdf504">here</a>.
    </p>
    <p>
      This is how a state-of-the art Hangprinter version 3 looked like in CAD on Apr 10, 2018, according to the repo:
    </p>
    <figure>
      <a href="./media/HP3_status_Apr_10_2018.png">
        <img src="./media/HP3_status_Apr_10_2018_small.png" alt="" width="500" height="304"/>
      </a>
      <figcaption>
        Click the image for a larger version.
        Although all parts were finished, this assembly file was admittedly not finished.
        Still, we can clearly see the intent of having motors offloaded from the effector.
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>
      This is how a state-of-the art Hangprinter version 2 looked like in CAD on Apr 10, 2018, according to the repo:
    </p>
    <figure>
      <a href="./media/HP2_status_Feb_12_2018.png">
        <img src="./media/HP2_status_Feb_12_2018_small.png" alt="" width="500" height="331"/>
      </a>
      <figcaption>
        Click the image for a larger version.
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <h2>Prior Art Published On Reprap Forums</h2>
    <h3>The First Thread</h3>
    <p>
      The first forum thread is ca 65 posts long, and ca 13 people took part in the open discussion.
      In it, I present the idea of a cable driven Reprap.
      You can find it <a href="https://reprap.org/forum/read.php?178,344022">here</a>.
    </p>
    <p>
      I will re-post some relevant images and quotes here.
      Not all quotes are mine, but all images are mine.
      All were posted between Apr 23, 2014 and Nov 14 2017.
      Further details are in the <a href="https://reprap.org/forum/read.php?178,344022">forum thread</a>.
    </p>
    <figure>
      <a href="./media/very_first_digital_sketch.png">
        <img src="./media/very_first_digital_sketch_small.png" alt="" width="500" height="317"/>
      </a>
      <figcaption>
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>
      <ul>
        <li>"... possibly introducing hardware to help keep the xy-plane wires tight..."</li>
        <li>"... The most compact ... out there."</li>
        <li>"... Extreme print heights ...</li>
        <li>"The only thing we control in this system, is the length of the three wires. Every possible combination of wire-lengths, (l0, l1, l2), corresponds to a unique point in the avilable print area (a triangle). To map a point (x', y') to the corresponding wire-lengths, all we have to do is place the wires anchor-points in the cartesian coordinate system, and compute the lengths from each anchor point to the point (x', y'). Like this:"</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <figure>
      <a href="./media/geometry_2d.gif">
        <img src="./media/geometry_2d.gif" alt="" width="500" height="500"/>
      </a>
      <figcaption>
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>
      <ul>
        <li>"Check out the <a href="https://designmakeshare.wordpress.com/2013/09/16/introducing-skydelta/">SkyDelta</a>."</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <p>
      It's worth pausing at the SkyDelta, and note that it too has striking similarities to the patented contraption.
      I won't go into the details here, but in the detailed blog post from 2013 linked above, Brandon Heller includes a video that
      shows similarities from an overview perspective:
    </p>
    <figure>
      <div class='embed-container'>
        <iframe src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/lnp1Pmki3lI'
          frameborder='0'
          allowfullscreen='true'
          allow='encrypted-media'>
        </iframe>
      </div>
      <figcaption>
        Brandon Heller's Youtube video from 2013.
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>
      Now let's continue to explore the first forum thread.
      <ul>
        <li>"A setup with a dedicated z-motor, and no springs at all. This will require the four motors to work against each other to keep the lines tight."</li>
        <li>"A sprung loaded Z motor. You then don't have to worry as much about getting all 4 motors perfectly in sync."</li>
        <li>"Might be an interesting concept for something like cement printing?"</li>
        <li>"You could sink poles and then string them like you would do a tent."</li>
        <li>"You could install it outside in a large area."</li>
        <li>"But generally this is the best concept for DIY house printing because you don't need large heavy and stiff frames or cranes."</li>
        <li>"The one action line going to the roof could be made triple and attached to each corner of the triangular print platform to handle forces downwards."</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <figure>
      <a href="./media/three_z_configuration.png">
        <img src="./media/three_z_configuration_small.png" alt="" width="500" height="476"/>
      </a>
      <figcaption>
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>
      <ul>
        <li>"I love the idea of being able to print a house!"</li>
        <li>"There's some students somewhere that executed something like this but they're printing with clay. Search "sky printer" on instructables."</li>
        <li>"... instead of three motors you can use only two and a spring-loaded rewinder or a weight at the free end of the wire."</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <h3>The Second Thread</h3>
    <p>
      ...
    </p>
  </post>
</posts>

<!---
  The patent long url:
https://patft.uspto.gov/netacgi/nph-Parser?Sect1=PTO1&Sect2=HITOFF&d=PALL&p=1&u=%2Fnetahtml%2FPTO%2Fsrchnum.htm&r=1&f=G&l=50&s1=11230032.PN.&OS=PN/11230032&RS=PN/11230032

more test printing KokoKaka: https://twitter.com/tobbelobb/status/963030599073255425

Version 2 forum thread: https://reprap.org/forum/read.php?1,738858
Version 3 forum thread: https://reprap.org/forum/read.php?423,792937

-->
