<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="blogtemplate.xsl"?>
<posts year="2022">
  <post id="prior_art_1" heading="Prior Art Relevant to Patent US 11230032" date="2-2-2022">
    <p>
      The <a href="https://wayfinder.digital/fedinvent/patents-2022/details-patents-20220125.html#11230032_DOE">patent in question</a> was filed on Apr 13, 2018.
      We will refer to the patented contraption as SkyBAAM, or "the patented contraption", for short.
      We will present prior art relevant to SkyBAAM, all of which was unmentioned and unreferenced in the patent.
      The prior art we present will mostly have been published within context of the open source project called Hangprinter.
    </p>
    <p>
      The patent contains many ideas that have been explored, published, and then discontinued within the Hangprinter community
      before Apr 13, 2018.
    </p>
    <p>
      This writing will be long and detailed.
      The corpus of relevant prior art published publicly before April 13 2018 is vast,
      since the Hangprinter Project was already four years old at the time.
      This prior art includes, but is not limited to:
      <ul>
        <li><a href="https://torbjornludvigsen.com/blog/2018/#hangprinter_project_55">56 technical blog posts</a></li>
        <li>Ca 350 posts on Reprap forums<ul>
            <li><a href="https://reprap.org/forum/read.php?178,344022">thread 1</a></li>
            <li><a href="https://reprap.org/forum/read.php?1,738858">thread 2</a></li>
            <li><a href="https://reprap.org/forum/read.php?423,792937">thread 3</a></li>
          </ul>
        </li>
        <li><a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/hangprinter">A few hundred posts in the Facebook group</a></li>
        <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/results?search_query=Hangprinter&amp;sp=CAI%253D">Ca 25 relevant Youtube videos</a></li>
        <li><a href="https://vimeo.com/user23166500">37 videos published on Vimeo</a></li>
        <li><a href="https://twitter.com/tobbelobb">Ca 100 Tweets</a></li>
        <li><a href="https://hangprinter.org/newsletter/">13 Hangprinter Newsletters</a></li>
        <li>Wiki articles on <a href="https://www.appropedia.org/Clerck,_a_RepRap_3D_printer_hanging_from_the_ceiling">Appropedia</a>, <a href="https://wiki.opensourceecology.org/wiki/Hangprinter">Open Source Ecology</a> and <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20180330041707/https://reprap.org/wiki/Hangprinter">Reprap Wiki</a>.</li>
        <!--li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hangprinter">Wikipedia</a></li-->
        <li><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20180405053344/http://hangprinter.org/">The hangprinter.org landing page</a></li>
        <!--li><a href="https://hangprinter.org/doc/v3/">Rich and visual documentation, created on April 10, 2018</a></li-->
        <li><a href="https://github.com/tobbelobb/hangprinter">A public Github repo containing over 500 relevant commits and issues</a></li>
        <li>A number of news articles, including but not limited to these
        <ul>
          <!--li><a href="https://www.3ders.org/articles/20170308-frameless-hangprinter-reprap-turns-an-entire-room-into-a-3d-printer.html">3ders.org</a></li-->
          <li><a href="https://hackaday.com/2017/03/20/hanging-3d-printer-uses-entire-room-as-print-bed/">hackaday.com</a></li>
          <li><a href="https://hackaday.com/2017/12/16/hangprinter-build-videos/">hackaday.com again</a></li>
          <li><a href="https://3dprintingindustry.com/news/interview-inventor-frameless-hangprinter-3d-printer-building-tower-babel-107749/">3dprintingindustry.com</a></li>
          <li><a href="https://www.seeker.com/open-source-prototype-turns-any-room-into-a-3d-printer-2313142390.html">seeker.com</a></li>
          <li><a href="https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2017/03/170308083723.htm">sciencedaily.com</a></li>
          <li><a href="https://www.fabbaloo.com/2017/03/the-hangprinter-a-frameless-3d-printer">fabbaloo.com</a></li>
          <li><a href="https://www.wired.com/beyond-the-beyond/2017/03/hangprinter-printer-just-sorta-hangs/">wired.com</a></li>
          <li><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170520051008/https://3dprint.com/167250/hangprinter-midair-3d-printer/">3dprint.com</a></li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      </ul>
      Note that all links in this post goes to previous art that was published publicly before April 13, 2018.
    </p>
    <br />
    <h2>Hangprinter References In the Patent</h2>
    <p>
      The patent made two references to Hangprinter:
      <ul>
        <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Hangprinter&amp;oldid=831632485">The English Wikipedia Article, who was mostly just a list of links at the time</a></li>
        <li><a href="https://www.3ders.org/articles/20170308-frameless-hangprinter-reprap-turns-an-entire-room-into-a-3d-printer.html">An out of date article from 3ders.org</a></li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <p>
      Those two sources alone do not cover enough details to reveal how deeply similar SkyBAAM is to the pre-existing Hangprinter.
      I will therefore present a selection of prior art here, picked from the long list above.
    </p>
    <p>
      I will comment on prior art that covers the highest level, most general ideas presented in the patent first,
      and slowly zoom in on technical details and implementation.
      However, some similarities are striking even at a long distance, without reference to technicalities, so I will cover those first.
    </p>
    <h2>Full Concept From A Distance</h2>
    <p>
      The Hangprinter prototype that was most visually similar to Fig 4 in the patent might be this
      early version 3 prototype, that was <a href="http://vitana.se/opr3d/tbear/2017#hangprinter_project_42">published and described in detail on April 4, 2017</a>.
    </p>
    <figure>
      <video width="500" controls="true">
        <source src="../2017/bilder/Freds_gopro.mp4" type="video/mp4"></source>
      </video>
      <figcaption>
        The video shows the first Hangprinter prototype that offloaded the motors and most of the electronics to one of the anchors.
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <figure>
      <a href="./media/Their_fig_4.png">
        <img src="./media/Their_fig_4_small.png" alt="" width="500" height="436"/>
      </a>
      <figcaption>
        Fig 4 from from the patent in question.
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <figure>
      <a href="./media/Their_fig_5.png">
        <img src="./media/Their_fig_5_small.png" alt="" width="500" height="403"/>
      </a>
      <figcaption>
        Fig 5 from from the patent in question.
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>
      What we see here is of course a very general machine.
      The fewer the lines in the sketch, the more general the machine.
      Like futuristic art, you fill in the rest with your fantasy.
    </p>
    <p>
      Formulations like the following make it sound like the patent covers the field of translational parallel cable driven robotics in its entirety:
      <ul>
        <li>"[...] an outdoor work site. Smaller-scale and/or indoor implementation are also contemplated"</li>
        <li>"one or more additional base stations"</li>
        <li>"one or more additional adjustable cables may be associated with any of the base stations"</li>
        <li>" the base stations 22A, 22B, 22C can include at least one pulley 42, multiple pulleys, or another suitable cable guide which route the cables 28A, 28B, 28C to change the direction of the force applied by the cables"</li>
        <li>"The various cables can be wound around their associated cable winders for transportation to a worksite"</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <p>
      The rest of us will have to continue our research on machines with three or less base stations,
      and cables that can't be wound around their associated cable winders for transportation, then.
      Or maybe it helps us to show that Hangprinter used between four and six lines in each direction already on July 5, 2017?
    </p>
    <figure>
      <div class='embed-container'>
        <iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/224390884"
            frameborder="0"
            webkitallowfullscreen="true"
            mozallowfullscreen="true"
            allowfullscreen="true">
        </iframe>
      </div>
      <figcaption>
        Video published August 1, 2017, demonstrating how additional lines in all directions help constrain rotational degrees of freedom,
        and I guess also its ability to "wind in its lines for transportation".
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>
      Oh well, maybe all <a href="https://github.com/MarlinFirmware/Marlin/issues/9101#issuecomment-356319633">previous public plans</a> to <a href="https://wiki.opensourceecology.org/wiki/Hangprinter#Anchor_Module">add more anchors to Hangprinter</a> must be scrapped?
      Or maybe it helps us that many <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7HNAL8ZKdyM">translational parallel cable driven robots</a> already had more than four anchor
      <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RCa8uDFzbsw">a long time before 13 Apr, 2018</a>?
    </p>
    <p>
      You never know.
      Let's stay nervous that something in this patent might still be valid, just to be on the safe side.
    </p>
    <p>
      Luckily, the patent later narrows itself down by specifying some things:
    </p>
    <p>
      "FIG 4. [...] three adjustable suspension cables 30 run from the aerial hoist 18 to the end effector 20, and perform the z-axis motion"
    </p>
    <p>
      Since "the fixed platform 34" is stationary,
      the formulation "z-axis motion" indicates that
      the end effector 20 can only move along a straight vertical line line.
      Like this:
    </p>
    <figure>
      <a href="./media/HP3_status_Apr_10_2018.png">
        <img src="./media/HP3_status_Apr_10_2018_small.png" alt="" width="500" height="304"/>
      </a>
      <figcaption>
        Hangprinter version 3, assembly file as it looked <a href="https://github.com/tobbelobb/hangprinter/tree/3fa54dbe37858ce02146a2d9f31bb17343fdf504">in the Hangprinter repo on Apr 10, 2018</a>.
        We were unaware at the time, that our machine, even in this stripped down form, could deserve a patent.
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>
      Oh well, that suddenly made the patent very narrow, bordering on the unexpected.
      Let's help the patent authors by assuming they made a mistake.
    </p>
    <p>
      After all, Fig 4 is only "another embodiment of a cable configuration for the cable-driven additive manufacturing system".
      So let's look closer for details that differentiates it from for example a Hangprinter.
    </p>
    <p>
      "One difference is that three adjustable suspension cables 30 run from the aerial hoist 18 to the end effector 20 [...] all run off one cable winder 32 [...] so that their length is always identical."
    </p>
    <p>
      I think they mean like this:
    </p>
    <figure>
      <div class='embed-container'>
        <iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/194813962"
            frameborder="0"
            webkitallowfullscreen="true"
            mozallowfullscreen="true"
            allowfullscreen="true">
        </iframe>
      </div>
      <figcaption>
        Video published Dec 8, 2016, demonstrating a worm drive on the D-axis on-board cable rewinder.
        We were unaware at the time that having three lines around a single spool could constitute an invention, so we didn't mention it, but it's clearly visible.
        The "cable rewinder" is onboard the end effector.
        The "aerial hoist" is shown, in the form of free hanging bearings, at the start of the video.
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>
      "This keeps the end effector 20 from tilting, which freezes two rotational DOF of the end effector 20."
    <p>
    </p>
      I'm unsure what is meant by "freezing", since degrees of freedom are independent of degrees of temperature.
      Ok, let's assume they made a mistake again.
      They surely meant "constrains two rotational DOF", right?
      Like this:
    </p>
    <figure>
      <a href="./media/Overview_rot.jpeg">
        <img src="./media/Overview_rot_small.jpeg" alt="" width="500" height="750"/>
      </a>
      <figcaption>
        Image of Hangprinter version 2 published on my blog <a href="https://torbjornludvigsen.com/blog/2016/#hangprinter_project_27">on 14 Dec, 2016</a>.
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>
      However, even if they meant "constrained", they would still be in error.
      Those rotational degrees of freedom are not constrained in either of their Figs 4 and 5.
      That's because they again narrow the scope of their patent by specifying that all cables, and hence anchors are in the x-y plane, like this:
    </p>
    <p>
      "... freezes all the rotational DOF [...].
      First, by putting more cables in the x-y plane, the stiffness of the system 14 is increased in the x-y plane."
    </p>
    <p>
      Oh gosh, with the top anchor only involved in z-axis movements, and all other cables in a flat plane, we're left with
      an end effector that's fixed in a single point, unable to move at all.
    </p>
    <p>
      It's peculiar how the patent's authors insist on keeping both lines and anchors in "the x-y plane".
      This will leave rotations around the x-axis and the y-axis unconstrained,
      since the "z-lines" can only pull upwards, and not push downwards.
    </p>
    <p>
      Even if the end effector is pulled in four directions at once, it's not being pulled downwards at all.
      The extrusion of material below it will eventually build up and push it upwards.
      This will cause rotation.
      The situation will look similar to this, but with concrete:
    </p>
    <figure>
      <a href="./media/disaster.jpeg">
        <img src="./media/disaster_small.jpeg" alt="" width="500" height="283"/>
      </a>
      <figcaption>
        This image is not previous art. It was <a href="https://twitter.com/tobbelobb/status/1186215813302439938">published too late, on Oct 21, 2019</a>.
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>
      I'm trying to assume that they're honestly trying to describe normal translational 3d movements, like other translational cable driven parallel robots do, but the patent's authors don't make it easy for me:
    </p>
    <p>
      "From the pulleys 42U, 42M, and 42L to the end effector, the cables 28U, 28L can run generally orthogonally to the support surface 60."
    </p>
    <p>
      The number 60 they're talking about, is the front plate of this thing:
    </p>
    <figure>
      <a href="./media/Their_fig_7.png">
        <img src="./media/Their_fig_7_small.png" alt="" width="500" height="427"/>
      </a>
      <figcaption>
        Fig 7 from from the patent in question.
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>
      So, if the cables 28U and 28L are orthogonal to the front plate 60, then the end effector can only move along a line that is parallel to plate 60's normal direction.
      With three different normal directions, this again constrains the end effector to stay put at a single point in space.
    </p>
    <p>
      In reality, the lines 28U and 28L will not stay orthogonal to 60, not even close, not even "generally".
    </p>
    <p>
      Let's assume the patent's authors made another mistake.
    </p>
    <p>
      Oh wait, by the way, doesn't that thing look eerly similar to that old Hangprinter 3 prototype 1 anchor?
    </p>
    <figure>
      <a href="./media/two_anchors.png">
        <img src="./media/two_anchors_small.png" alt="" width="500" height="338"/>
      </a>
      <figcaption>
        Two happy anchors waiting for the third one to be produced.
        This is screenshot from the video at the top of this post, who shows how they're used.
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>
      Never mind, they get back on track, by specifying:
    </p>
    <p>
      "In one embodiment, at least a portion of the base station 22 can telescope to raise the pulleys 42U, 42M, and 42L."
    </p>
    <p>
      So we're back up to one embodiement of their patented contraption that can carry out linear vertical motions,
      by utilizing a total of at least 7 motors.
    </p>
    <p>
      The telescopes are supposed to act like linear vertical axes, that can lift the pivot points of the lower lines.
      Kind of like this:
    </p>
    <figure>
      <a href="./media/baez.png">
        <img src="./media/baez_small.png" alt="" width="500" height="415"/>
      </a>
      <figcaption>
        A small Hangprinter version 3, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/hangprinter/posts/296884167488416">published by Antonio Baez in the Facebook group on Dec 18, 2017</a>.
        We see the lower lines being lifted by black v-shaped bearings, attached to yellow carriages that travel along linear rails.
        The yellow carriages seem to not be motorized in "this embodiment of" Hangprinter version 3.
        In another embodiment, it actually uses its highest motor to lift the other ones if needed.
        Never seen in reality though.
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>
      While we're on the topic of number of motors. They suggest increasing the number to at least 8 or 10, like this:
    </p>
    <p>
      "The base station 22 can optionally include a cable winder 50 for a suspension cable 30 used to adjust the position of an aerial hoist 18 (FIG. 8)."
    </p>
    <p>
      I feel like we're increasing the scope of this patent again.
      Let's look at FIG. 8 and FIG. 2.
    </p>
    <figure>
      <a href="./media/Their_fig_2.png">
        <img src="./media/Their_fig_2_small.png" alt="" width="500" height="325"/>
      </a>
      <figcaption>
        Fig 2 from from the patent in question.
        The "aerial hoist" is number 18.
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <figure>
      <a href="./media/Their_fig_8.png">
        <img src="./media/Their_fig_8_small.png" alt="" width="500" height="429"/>
      </a>
      <figcaption>
        Fig 8 from from the patent in question.
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>
      So, the "aerial hoist" does the same job as the v-shaped bearings in this image, from a previously presented video:
    </p>
    <figure>
      <a href="./media/aerial_hoist.png">
        <img src="./media/aerial_hoist_small.png" alt="" width="500" height="415"/>
      </a>
      <figcaption>
        The "aerial hoist" of Hangprinter verision 2.
        The cable rewinder is situated on the end effector itself.
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>
      However, the "aerial hoist" in the Fig 8 redirects the line towards an anchor ("base station"),
      so that all motors can potentially be located at ground level, like this:
    </p>
    <figure>
      <a href="./media/baez_1.jpg">
        <img src="./media/baez_1_small.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="415"/>
      </a>
      <figcaption>
        A Hangprinter with the "ceiling unit" placed on the floor, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/hangprinter/posts/288931208283712">published by Antonio Baez in the Facebook group on Nov 29, 2017</a>. Baez mainly uses lamp hooks to reroute the lines.
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>
      But there's one last peculiar thing about Fig 8.
      It includes springs (74) between the top hook and the cables.
    </p>
    <p>
      Introducing springs here and there to keep lines tight is a common beginner's mistake when designing Hangprinters,
      because it reduces positional control, limits maximum speeds and accelerations, and introduces eigenfrequencies in the motion system.
      It has <a href="https://reprap.org/forum/read.php?178,344022,345158#msg-345158">been discussed</a> many times, but never introduced into Hangprinter.
    </p>
    <p>
      However, earlier open source translational cable driven parallel robots did use springs,
      like for example this one:
    </p>
    <figure>
      <div class='embed-container'>
        <iframe src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/lnp1Pmki3lI'
          frameborder='0'
          allowfullscreen='true'
          allow='encrypted-media'>
        </iframe>
      </div>
      <figcaption>
        Brandon Heller's Youtube video from 2013 predates Hangprinter.
        Like most cable driven translation robots, Hangprinter included,
        it uses pairs of cables that are "generally parallel to each other" as it's formulated in the patent.
        It also uses rubber bands to pull upwards in much the same way as the patented contraption uses its springs.
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>
      But I have another problem with Fig 2.
      It's overly ambitious idea of 3d printing the Colluseum is just so darn similar
      to my own 2017 Babel tower project:
    </p>
    <figure>
      <a href="./media/Babylon2.jpeg">
        <img src="./media/Babylon2_small.jpeg" alt="" width="500" height="333"/>
      </a>
      <figcaption>
          This image was published <a href="https://vitana.se/opr3d/tbear/2017#hangprinter_project_33">in a blog post on 24 Feb, 2017</a>.
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <figure>
      <a href="./media/Their_fig_2.png">
        <img src="./media/Their_fig_2_small.png" alt="" width="500" height="325"/>
      </a>
      <figcaption>
        Fig 2 from from the patent in question.
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <figure>
      <video width="500" controls="true">
        <source src="./media/front_page_hangprinter-org_2.mp4" type="video/mp4"></source>
      </video>
      <figcaption>
          The video shows how the 3d animation covering
        <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170421035011/http://hangprinter.org/">hangprinter.org's front page for a full year before the patent in question was filed</a>.
        <a href="https://twitter.com/tobbelobb/status/849040245593165824">hangprinter.org was launched on Apr 4, 2017</a>,
          and the animation was there until it was <a href="https://twitter.com/tobbelobb/status/1308064219355648002">replaced on 21 Sep, 2020</a>.
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>
      The artistic expression (as well as the physical implementation),
      of an unfinished circular tower with tall arched windows,
      and a thick helical structure along the outer wall,
      being 3d printed by a cable driven parallel robot with four cable-directions,
      one of which is near vertical,
      driving an effector with rotational degrees of freedom being constrained by pairs of generally parallel cables,
      of which anchors (called base stations in the patent) are potentially lifted above ground level with thin tall structures,
      was published widely on all 3d printing news sites in Feb/March 2017, a year before the patent was filed.
    </p>
    <p>
      Images of this Babel tower were published on every 3d printingn news site in March 2017, including but not limited to:
      <ul>
        <li><a href="https://www.fabbaloo.com/2017/03/the-hangprinter-a-frameless-3d-printer">fabbaloo.com</a></li>
        <li><a href="https://www.3dnatives.com/de/hangprinter-3d-drucker-1003171/#!">3dnatives.com</a></li>
        <li><a href="https://www.archdaily.com/866985/umea-university-develops-low-cost-flexible-3d-printer">archdaily.com</a></li>
        <li><a href="https://3dprintingindustry.com/news/interview-inventor-frameless-hangprinter-3d-printer-building-tower-babel-107749/">3dprintingindustry.com</a></li>
        <li><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170520051008/https://3dprint.com/167250/hangprinter-midair-3d-printer/">3dprint.com</a></li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <h2>But How About Houses, Scaling Up, Using Concrete, Using A Crane?</h2>
    <p>
      Just to be clear, the history of the Babel tower in the Holy Bible does not describe
      a 40 x 40 cm tower that was 4.6 m tall.
      The printed Babel tower on the images above is a scaled down version of the Babel tower
      I had in mind.
      The idea of scaling up a small Babel tower is not an invention in my humble opinion.
    </p>
    <p>
      The idea of printing with cement <a href="https://reprap.org/forum/read.php?178,344022,444205#msg-444205">
      appeared already on the first page of the first forum thread about Hangprinter back in 2014</a>,
      and has kept appearing at a rate of every fiftieth forum post or so suggesting it.
      My reply was that <a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/hangprinter/posts/342461566264009/?comment_id=342592839584215">beefing up the parts should be straightforward</a>.
    </p>
    <p>
      Scaling up is among the first two benefits I mention in the very first blog post about Hangprinter, from <a href="https://vitana.se/opr3d/tbear/2014.html#Hangprinter">May 15, 2014</a>.
    </p>
    <figure>
      <a href="./media/First_two_benefits.png">
        <img src="./media/First_two_benefits.png" alt="" width="500" height="66"/>
      </a>
      <figcaption>
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>
      Apart from <a href="https://github.com/MarlinFirmware/Marlin/pull/9180#issuecomment-369829924">being very obvious</a>,
      the general idea of "<a href="https://reprap.org/forum/read.php?178,344022,445524#msg-445524">3d printing houses with Hangprinters</a>, <a href="https://reprap.org/forum/read.php?1,738858,760264#msg-760264">out of concrete</a>, while hanging from cranes"
      was frequently discussed in public around 2017 and 2018.
      One of the more entertaining conversations included these visuals.
    </p>
    <figure>
      <a href="./media/crane_on_facebook_2018-03-17-20:02:41.png">
        <img src="./media/crane_on_facebook_2018-03-17-20:02:41_small.png" alt="" width="500" height="281"/>
      </a>
      <figcaption>
        Click the image for a larger version.
        Screenshot from the Facebook group called "Hangprinter - RepRap Project " on March 17, 2018.
        A person called Ed Aylward posted visuals, related to the common idea of scaling up Hangprinter for printing concrete buildings, in the Facebook group, stating patent pending on the idea.
        The idea of "crane with wheels" is discussed in the conversation.
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>
      The group had <a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/hangprinter/posts/194019467774887/">over 200 members and increasing, already a year earlier</a>.
      This was a big public group with very active discussion about Hangprinter.
    </p>
    <p>
      The web page that Mr Aylward linked to in his post was <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20180228165805/https://p3d.in/O6NBW+welcome">saved by Wayback Machine on 28 Feb, 2018</a>,
        so he had clearly created it at least a few days before posting publicly.
      At the time of writing this, <a href="https://p3d.in/O6NBW">the web page is still up</a>.
    </p>
    <figure>
      <a href="./media/Aylwards_web_page2.png">
        <img src="./media/Aylwards_web_page2_small.png" alt="" width="500" height="399"/>
      </a>
      <figcaption>
        Click the image for a larger version.
        An illustration of the frequent and common idea of 3d printing a concrete house with Hangprinter, screendumped from Aylward's publicly linked web site.
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>
      It was, for the longest time unclear whether the "invention" in these visuals was to
      <ul>
        <li>Scale up a toy, or to</li>
        <li>scale down the idea of a crane.</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <p>
      Luckily, Mr Aylward included an object of known size in his 3d visualization:
    </p>
    <figure>
      <a href="./media/HP1_Aylwards_web_page.png">
        <img src="./media/HP1_Aylwards_web_page_small.png" alt="" width="500" height="274"/>
      </a>
      <figcaption>
        Click the image for a larger version.
        Aylward's web page displays 3d graphics, and lets us zoom in on the displayed object.
        We can see that this is Hangprinter version 1, and not version 2, because it does not yet use a worm gear for its D-axis (mostly vertical axis), like the Hangprinter version 2 did.
        If we search through Github's catalouge, we can probably pin down when it was downloaded because it includes a distinct bug:
        there are two motors with "B-gears", both driving the "B-lines" in the render.
        That bug would make the machine not work as intended in practice, and was probably removed soon after, in the real Hangprinter repo.
        The three low anchors are also identical to those published as Hangprinter version 1 anchors in the Hangprinter repo.
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>
      This would imply that the "invention" was a combination of the two above.
      A very large toy truck pushing a cylinder down through a standard Hangprinter via a very small crane.
    </p>
    <p>
      No, of course I understand that the cylinder would contain un-cured concrete, and the very large Hangprinter would be printing a concrete shell for a house.
    </p>
    <h2>But The Super Smart Tension Control Described In the Patent, How About That?</h2>
    <p>
      I assume they mean torque control, as it's called in Hangprinter circles?
      All Hangprinter anchors have tension control.
    </p>
    <figure>
      <div class='embed-container'>
        <iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/227891846"
            frameborder="0"
            webkitallowfullscreen="true"
            mozallowfullscreen="true"
            allowfullscreen="true">
        </iframe>
      </div>
      <figcaption>
        Video published August 1, 2017.
        Since torque mode (tension control) only controls the torque of the motors (and hence the tension of the cables),
        the en effector will move if you drag it by hand.
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>
      Torque mode is a standard feature since 2017.
      It's very practical when you start the printer up and want to move the end effector
      safely and rapidly without thinking too much.
    </p>
    <p>
      It's also used during auto-calibration (automatic anchor localization within the xyz coordinate system).
      During auto calibration it's common for a Hangprinter to mix the normal "position mode" with torque mode,
      frequently switching modes for individual motors.
    </p>
    <p>
      An advanced non-linear minimization algorith is applied to transform the set of collected quadruples of motor positions,
      into a set of four anchor locations.
      The version of the algorithm that was available on Apr 13, 2018 can be found here: <a href="https://gitlab.com/tobben/auto-calibration-simulation-for-hangprinter/-/tree/a3e7878987f88ff29ca2785d49390a34414e9027">auto-calibration-simulation-for-hangprinter</a>.
    </p>
    <h2>But SkyBAAM Has Its Cable Rewinders At The Base Stations! Hangprinter Does Not</h2>
    <p>
      This is another discussion that has kept coming back at a rate of ca one out of fifty forum posts.
      <a href="https://reprap.org/forum/read.php?1,738858,746545#msg-746545">The following one is from Feb 2017</a>:
    </p>
    <p>
      <ul>
        <li><font color="blue">MechaBits</font>: "Was there a reason you never went with the motors on the walls?"</li>
        <li><font color="red">tobben</font>:     "Yup several reasons, of course. One of them is that I have to tidy up after me each time I've used the printer. <i> [part of quote left out for brevity] ...</i>"</li>
        <li><font color="blue">MechaBits</font>: "But surely you could also do that with motors on the walls."</li>
        <li><font color="red">tobben</font>:     "Quite possible, of course. I'd love to see such a solution."</li>
        <li><font color="blue">MechaBits</font>: "I would have thought you where in a better position to mentally picture what it would look like, due to your experience with this."</li>
        <li><font color="red">tobben</font>:     "Oh yes, you would have to choose between synchronizing steppers wirelessly, drive them from a stationary PCB or to find a smart way to wind stepper cables. <br /><br />Last alternative first: You could carry the stepper drivers and the microcontroller on the moving part. Signal noise because of the stepper cable lengths would be no (or a very small) problem, but they will of course have weight. You could wind in the motors when not in use and park everything in the ceiling. Nice. <br /><br />Wireless motor control is probably the best solution for very big high-performance machines. You must do more programming, need more PCBs and more power supplies. The PCBs could be placed almost anywhere and you don't need to hide a lot of ugly cables. Semi nice. <br /><br />
With one stationary PCB and long cables to stationary motors, it will be a lot of work to make it look tidy. You will have to transform your entire room into a RepRap frame. If quick and dirty solutions, like cables taped to the floor/ceiling, works for you, and if you never need your room for something else, then this solution gives you the most print performance for your time and your buck. Or at least, that's my guess."</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <p>
      In my humble opinion, moving the motors to the anchors is a very obvious thing to do for anyone wanting to scale up Hangprinter.
      For example Open Source Ecology had this on their Hangprinter wiki page already on 17 Dec, 2017:
    </p>
    <figure>
      <a href="./media/OSE_10.png">
        <img src="./media/OSE_10_small.png" alt="" width="500" height="436"/>
      </a>
      <figcaption>
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>
      Open Source Ecology seemed to think that Hangprinter was already being used for 3d printing of buildings.
      They also knew that "Keep Motors on the anchor stations" was a prerequisite for a minimal viable product.
    </p>
    <p>
      Note that Open Source Ecology, and <a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/hangprinter/posts/181973192312848/">all the others</a> that <a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/hangprinter/posts/212829602560540/">suggested locating the motors at the various anchor points</a> back in 2017 and early 2018, in all the links are <a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/hangprinter/posts/208550112988489">laymen trying to help out</a>,
      not even having "ordinary skill in the art" of cable driven robotics.
      That's how obvious these ideas are.
    </p>
    <h2>What About the Guy Wires?</h2>
    <p>
      The patent in question describes guy wires going from the D-anchor (high-up) anchor down to the anchors (base stations) with tension in them to pull
      the D-anchor downwards and outwards, and hence stabilizing it.
      See for example lines 36 in Fig 4 from their patent, near the top of this web page.
    </p>
    <p>
      We have never used the terms "guy-wire" or "suspension wire" much in the Hangprinter community.
      However, we've had lines going between the D-anchor and the lower anchors, just like guy wires would, since April 2017.
      See for example the video posted at the top of this article, or this image that was published on Dec 7, 2017:
    </p>
    <figure>
      <a href="./media/people_want_to_reprap.JPG">
        <img src="./media/people_want_to_reprap_small.JPG" alt="" width="500" height="749"/>
      </a>
      <figcaption>
        Click the image for a larger version.
        Hangprinter version 3 being demonstrated on Maker Fair Rome in December 2017.
        Lines pulling the D-anchor down towards all three low anchors, with fixated start points and end points, are visible in the image
        against the white background.
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <figure>
      <a href="./media/nick_scott_Feb_9_2018_facebook_group_small.jpg">
        <img src="./media/nick_scott_Feb_9_2018_facebook_group_small.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="667"/>
      </a>
      <figcaption>
        This render was <a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/hangprinter/posts/320622445114588/">uploaded on Feb 9, 2018, by Nick Scott, to the public Hangprinter group on Facebook</a>.
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>
      Although Hangprinter's guy wires are rerouted to also serve as transmitting motion forces to the end effector,
      these lines double up to do the same guy-wire pulling as the static cables mentioned in the patent would do,
      as long as all the lines are always tight, which they always are since the machine would otherwise loose
      control over the effectors translational movement.
    </p>
    <p>
      Some might believe that the SkyBAAM's guy wires would have a constant tension in them, but in fact they would not have constant tension.
      The tension in the SkyBAAM's guy wires would vary greatly depending on variation in the pulling force from above, and depending on
      where within the build volume (called W in the patent) were at any given time, because the end effector is connected to the D-anchor (highest anchor),
      where the guy wires are also connected.
      Therefore, the conceptual difference between the SkyBAAM's guy wires and Hangprinter's guy wires is only superficial if at all.
    </p>
    <p>
      So even though it might look like Hangprinter doesn't need guy wires, it does have them, as part of a dual purpose line routing configuration.
    </p>


    <h2>But The UHMWPE Wires Then? Does Hangprinter Have Them?</h2>
    <p>
      Yes. Hangprinter has never used anything else.
      See for example this <a href="https://www.appropedia.org/w/index.php?title=Clerck,_a_RepRap_3D_printer_hanging_from_the_ceiling&amp;oldid=318273#Costs">Bill Of Materials List from Dec 9, 2015</a>.
    </p>
    <p>
      Ok, so we've been having some fun.
      However, the similarities between the patented contraption and Hangprinter are not merely superficial.
      We can dive deeper, and ask questions like:
    </p>
    <h2>But Was The Repo Publicly Available?</h2>
    <p>
      The general public had access and usage rights to the repo continously at all times since Dec 15, 2014, including on Apr 13, 2018.
    </p>
    <p>
      Information about how popular and well known the repo was on Apr 13, 2018 can be found by using <a href="http://archive.org">archive.org</a>, also known as Wayback Machine.
      It is a service that stores and archives old web pages, so we can visit them again, and see exactly how they looked on given dates,
      superficially similar to how the git/Github saving and catalouging works.
      However, it does not save every web page every day, so the investigated dates will precede Apr 13, 2018 by weeks or months.
    </p>
    <p>
      This is how github.com/tobbelobb/hangprinter looked on Jun 26, 2017:
    </p>
    <figure>
      <a href="./media/Jun26_2017_Github.png">
        <img src="./media/Jun26_2017_Github_small.png" alt="" width="500" height="276"/>
      </a>
      <figcaption>
        Click the image for a larger version.
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>
      In the image we can see that the repo had 77 watchers, 248 stars, and 49 forks.
      This means that this was a popular repo at the time.
      The 49 forks means that at least 49 people have copied Hangprinter's source files
      to use as the basis for their own cable driven robot build.
    </p>
    <p>
      The license in the repo allows and encourages such copying.
      Hangprinter was the most popular and widely known basis for cable driven robot development in 2017 and 2018.
    </p>
    <h3>And We Can Go Deeper...</h3>
    <p>
      Although the patent doesn't mention kinematics transforms in detail, I will mention Hangprinter's briefly here,
      to make the case that Hangprinter was capable of doing a superset of the effector movements that the authors envision in the patent.
    </p>
    <figure>
      <a href="./media/inverse_transform.png">
        <img src="./media/inverse_transform_small.png" alt="" width="500" height="535"/>
      </a>
      <figcaption>
        Click the image for a larger version.
        We see here that Hangprinter calculates its desired line lenghts by using Pythagoras' theorem on all its four cable directions.
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>
      The anchors can therefore be placed at arbitrary positions around the print volume, and the firmware will still work.
    </p>
    <p>
      The values of <code>anchor_A_z</code>, <code>anchor_B_z</code>, and <code>anchor_C_z</code> describe the z-positions of the three normally lower placed anchors.
      These three values, as well as all the other anchor position values, can be changed mid-print, as evindenced by the widely covered 2017 tall tower print.
    </p>
    <figure>
      <div class='embed-container'>
        <iframe src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/h6k4aVsbUOk'
          frameborder='0'
          allowfullscreen='true'
          allow='encrypted-media'>
        </iframe>
      </div>
      <figcaption>
        In this video from Apr 15, 2017, it's clear that the lines are terminated at different z-heights during different parts of the print.
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>
      All of these firmware features were <a href="https://github.com/MarlinFirmware/Marlin/pull/9180#issuecomment-380536959">being merged into the world's most used firmware at the time</a>,
      called Marlin Firmware, in a public merge thread (similar to a forum thread) that was publicly available and open for anyone to read and participate in.
      This means Hangprinter and all its features were becoming an integrated and widely available type of 3d printer at the firmware level at the time before April 13, 2018.
    </p>
    <!--p>
      There's also an <a href="https://github.com/MarlinFirmware/Marlin/issues/9101">earlier merge thread</a> with important info.
      Comments made publicly on Jan 9, 2018 relate to the obvious idea of adding more motion axes (called "cable rewinders" in the patent) than four to Hangprinter.
      <ul>
        <li>"... It's would also give us trouble the day want to add a fifth motion axis, and a couple more extruders, which is not unlikely."</li>
        <li>"... This would allow fifth and sixth motion axes, along with additional extruders, to be easily added, but it would take some more work to implement."</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <h2>Prior Art Published On Reprap Forums</h2>
    <h3>The First Thread</h3>
    <p>
      The first forum thread is 63 posts long, and 15 people took part in the open discussion.
      In it, I present the idea of a cable driven Reprap.
      You can find it <a href="https://reprap.org/forum/read.php?178,344022">here</a>.
    </p>
    <p>
      I will re-post some relevant images and quotes here in chronological order.
      Not all quotes are mine, but all images are mine.
      All were posted between Apr 23, 2014 and Nov 14 2017.
      Further details are in the <a href="https://reprap.org/forum/read.php?178,344022">forum thread</a>.
    </p>
    <figure>
      <a href="./media/very_first_digital_sketch.png">
        <img src="./media/very_first_digital_sketch_small.png" alt="" width="500" height="317"/>
      </a>
      <figcaption>
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>
      <ul>
        <li>"... possibly introducing hardware to help keep the xy-plane wires tight..."</li>
        <li>"... The most compact ... out there."</li>
        <li>"... Extreme print heights ..."</li>
        <li>"The only thing we control in this system, is the length of the three wires. Every possible combination of wire-lengths, (l0, l1, l2), corresponds to a unique point in the avilable print area (a triangle). To map a point (x', y') to the corresponding wire-lengths, all we have to do is place the wires anchor-points in the cartesian coordinate system, and compute the lengths from each anchor point to the point (x', y'). Like this:"</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <figure>
      <a href="./media/geometry_2d.gif">
        <img src="./media/geometry_2d.gif" alt="" width="500" height="500"/>
      </a>
      <figcaption>
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>
      <ul>
        <li>"Check out the <a href="https://designmakeshare.wordpress.com/2013/09/16/introducing-skydelta/">SkyDelta</a>."</li>
        <li>"A setup with a dedicated z-motor, and no springs at all. This will require the four motors to work against each other to keep the lines tight."</li>
        <li>"A sprung loaded Z motor. You then don't have to worry as much about getting all 4 motors perfectly in sync."</li>
        <li>"Might be an interesting concept for something like cement printing?"</li>
        <li>"You could sink poles and then string them like you would do a tent."</li>
        <li>"You could install it outside in a large area."</li>
        <li>"But generally this is the best concept for DIY house printing because you don't need large heavy and stiff frames or cranes."</li>
        <li>"The one action line going to the roof could be made triple and attached to each corner of the triangular print platform to handle forces downwards."</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <figure>
      <a href="./media/three_z_configuration.png">
        <img src="./media/three_z_configuration_small.png" alt="" width="500" height="476"/>
      </a>
      <figcaption>
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>
      <ul>
        <li>"I love the idea of being able to print a house!"</li>
        <li>"There's some students somewhere that executed something like this but they're printing with clay. Search "sky printer" on instructables."</li>
        <li>"... instead of three motors you can use only two and a spring-loaded rewinder or a weight at the free end of the wire."</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <h3>The Second Thread</h3>
    <p>
      The second forum thread is 247 posts long, and 19 people took part in the open discussion.
      In it, I present and support the development of the Hangprinter version 2.
      You can find it <a href="https://reprap.org/forum/read.php?1,738858">here</a>.
    </p>
    <p>
      I will re-post some relevant images and quotes here in chronological order.
      Not all quotes are mine, but all images are mine.
      All were posted between Jan 14, 2017 and Dec 16 2017.
      Further details are in the <a href="https://reprap.org/forum/read.php?1,738858">forum thread</a>.
    </p>
    <p>
      <ul>
        <li>"I think that this configuration lends itself very well to multimodal output drawing, laser CNC and 3d printing."</li>
      </ul>
      Then there's a discussion about where to place the motors (and therefore wire winches):
      <ul>
        <li><font color="blue">MechaBits</font>: "Was there a reason you never went with the motors on the walls?"</li>
        <li><font color="red">tobben</font>:     "Yup several reasons, of course. One of them is that I have to tidy up after me each time I've used the printer. <i> [part of quote left out for brevity] ...</i>"</li>
        <li><font color="blue">MechaBits</font>: "But surely you could also do that with motors on the walls."</li>
        <li><font color="red">tobben</font>:     "Quite possible, of course. I'd love to see such a solution."</li>
        <li><font color="blue">MechaBits</font>: "I would have thought you where in a better position to mentally picture what it would look like, due to your experience with this."</li>
        <li><font color="red">tobben</font>:     "Oh yes, you would have to choose between synchronizing steppers wirelessly, drive them from a stationary PCB or to find a smart way to wind stepper cables. <br /><br />

Last alternative first: You could carry the stepper drivers and the microcontroller on the moving part. Signal noise because of the stepper cable lengths would be no (or a very small) problem, but they will of course have weight. You could wind in the motors when not in use and park everything in the ceiling. Nice. <br /><br />

Wireless motor control is probably the best solution for very big high-performance machines. You must do more programming, need more PCBs and more power supplies. The PCBs could be placed almost anywhere and you don't need to hide a lot of ugly cables. Semi nice. <br /><br />

With one stationary PCB and long cables to stationary motors, it will be a lot of work to make it look tidy. You will have to transform your entire room into a RepRap frame. If quick and dirty solutions, like cables taped to the floor/ceiling, works for you, and if you never need your room for something else, then this solution gives you the most print performance for your time and your buck. Or at least, that's my guess."</li>
      </ul>
      <ul>
        <li>"Have you thought about the use of a laser pointer or rangefinder aimed at the corner that would give a digital distance to the computer? More expense that way. I have seen IR sensors that can determine distance for about 20 dollars."</li>
        <li>"I've thought about multiple different distance measurement solutions. My pet idea right now is using draw-wire displacement sensors like this: <i>[omitted]</i> ... in combination with accelerometer/gyro like described here:  <i>[omitted]</i>"</li>
        <li>"Sensors that allow an automatic calibration and/or homing procedure. Many sensor setups could achieve this:<br />
            <ol type="1"><li> Metal tubes on each line that can close a circuit</li><li> Accelerometer+gyro (IMU) units</li><li> Sound sensing (maybe 1 mic + 5 speakers)</li><li> Draw-wire displacement sensors in each direction</li><li> Optical sensing from salvaged computer mice</li><li> Small touchpad area on the build plate. For example calibrating and homing with a tablet or smart phone below print head."</li></ol></li>
        <li>"Note that both the stl and the above image shows doubled lines along all axes (for mechanical advantage). <i>[part of quite ommitted ...]</i> If you want double mechanical advantage along A, B and C, you must specify that in Configuration.h"</li>
      </ul>
      We then discussed placement of anchors:
      <ul>
        <li><font color="blue">L0g4n</font>: " ... why not put the anchor points on the ceiling as well?"</li>
      </ul>
    <figure>
      <a href="./media/three_high_anchors.jpg">
        <img src="./media/three_high_anchors_small.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="375"/>
      </a>
      <figcaption>
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
      <ul>
        <li><font color="blue">L0g4n</font>: " ... why not put the anchor points on the ceiling as well?"</li>
        <li><font color="red">tobben</font>: "The setup to the right would work well, especially when lines are at a ca 45 degree angle. My main reasons for not choosing it for Hangprinter was<br />
          <ul>
            <li>Accelerations are limited by gravity. Maximum acceleration is equal to that of a pendulum.</li>
            <li>Slightly trickier to park in the ceiling when not in use."</li>
          </ul></li>
      </ul>
        Then a comment on placement of motors, and printing of houses with concrete again.
      <ul>
        <li>"If you placed he motors on the frame that would give you a lighter carriage with potentially faster kinematic speeds."</li>
        <li>"you can build complete houses with a big enough setup and a concrete dispenser as tool"</li>
      </ul>
        Next followed a question that touches upon some of the claims presented in the patent
      <ul>
        <li><font color="blue">L0g4n</font>: "did you consider using just a single vertical line and account for the sled tilt due to the tension in the side lines in the math?"</li>
        <li><font color="red">tobben</font>: "No, I never thought about this. Hangprinter currently doesn't measure tension. It measures nothing other than hot end temp. Looking forward to see a lot of sensor experimentation!"</li>
      </ul>
        Next we mentioned the constant force mode, later called torque mode:
      <ul>
        <li>"It's also possible to drive steppers in constant force mode =) See the Mechaduino Project and some ongoing discussion about that here: [<a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/hangprinter/permalink/185601638616670/">www.facebook.com</a>]"</li>
      </ul>

    </p>
    <p>
      TODO: Have only searched through pages 1, 2, 3...
    </p>

    <h2>Prior Art Published On in the Facebook Group</h2>

    <h3>Comments on Edward Aylward's Crane Visuals</h3>
    <p>
      The idea of 3d printing houses with Hangprinter was frequently discussed in the Hangprinter Facebook group around 2017 and 2018.
      At least one of these conversations included some visuals.
    </p>
    <figure>
      <a href="./media/crane_on_facebook_2018-03-17-20:02:41.png">
        <img src="./media/crane_on_facebook_2018-03-17-20:02:41_small.png" alt="" width="500" height="281"/>
      </a>
      <figcaption>
        Click the image for a larger version.
        Screenshot from the Facebook group called "Hangprinter - RepRap Project " on March 17, 2018.
        A person called Ed Aylward posted visuals, related to the common idea of scaling up Hangprinter for printing concrete buildings, in the Facebook group, stating patent pending on the idea.
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>
      I will point out some important details in the image above.
      In the top right corner, we see the computer displayed the current date at the time: "Sat Mar 17 20:02".
      The year 2018 is confirmed in the bottom right, where it says: "Facebook  2018"
    </p>
    <p>
      In the top left corner, it says "public group".
      The group had <a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/hangprinter/posts/194019467774887/">over 200 members and increasing, already a year earlier</a>.
      This was a big public group with very active discussion about Hangprinter.
    </p>
    <p>
      Here's a part of the conversation in the screendump, suggesting a crane with wheels, as we saw in the SkyBAAM patent:
      <ul>
        <li><font color="blue">Jeff Smith</font>: "Crane looks a bit more permanent than the building... You know they make those with wheels right?"</li>
        <li><font color="green">Ed Aylward</font>: "yes of course"    </li>
        <li><font color="red">tobben</font>: "Mr Aylward has emailed me three times before, with talk of getting rich through a patent.<br /><br />
          You are welcome to get rich from using Hangprinter, Mr. Aylward. It is my honest opinion that you are wasting your time with this patent nonsense.<br /><br />
          I have no money, you if you plan to sue me there is nothing there for you to win. As indicated by the above conversation, you will spend your time fighting the Hangprinter Community, not with getting rich."</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <p>
      Below the conversation, we see that Mr Aylward had posted two hours earlier:
      <li>A link to a web page</li>
      <li>An image</li>
      <li>A text: "3D CONCRETE BUILDING PRINTER. INVESTORS WANTED. Patents Pending, All rights reserved. (not to scale)"</li>
    </p>
    <p>
      The web page that Mr Aylward linked to in his post was <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20180228165805/https://p3d.in/O6NBW+welcome">saved by Wayback Machine on 28 Feb, 2018</a>,
        so he had clearly created it at least a few days before posting publicly.
      At the time of writing this, <a href="https://p3d.in/O6NBW">the web page is still up</a>.
    </p>
    <figure>
      <a href="./media/edward_aylwards_page.png">
        <img src="./media/edward_aylwards_page_small.png" alt="" width="500" height="284"/>
      </a>
      <figcaption>
        Click the image for a larger version.
        The web page linked in Mr Aylward's public post.
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>
      The linked web page, as well as the image posted in the public facebook group, showed a 3d model of Hangprinter version 1,
      that had been copied straight from the Hangprinter repo
    </p>
    <figure>
      <a href="./media/HP1_Aylwards_web_page.png">
        <img src="./media/HP1_Aylwards_web_page_small.png" alt="" width="500" height="274"/>
      </a>
      <figcaption>
        Click the image for a larger version.
        Aylward's web page displays 3d graphics, and lets us zoom in on the displayed object.
        We can see that this is Hangprinter version 1, and not version 2, because it does not yet use a worm gear for its D-axis (mostly vertical axis), like the Hangprinter version 2 did.
        If we search through Github's catalouge, we can probably pin down when it was downloaded because it includes a distinct bug:
        there are two motors with "B-gears", both driving the "B-lines" in the render.
        That bug would make the machine not work as intended in practice, and was probably removed soon after, in the real Hangprinter repo.
        The three low anchors are also identical to those published as Hangprinter version 1 anchors in the Hangprinter repo.
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <figure>
      <a href="./media/Aylwards_web_page2.png">
        <img src="./media/Aylwards_web_page2_small.png" alt="" width="500" height="399"/>
      </a>
      <figcaption>
        Click the image for a larger version.
        An illustration of the frequent and common idea of 3d printing a concrete house with Hangprinter, screendumped from Aylward's publicly linked web site.
      </figcaption>
    </figure>
    <p>
      Searching with Google Patents and <a href="https://ppubs.uspto.gov/pubwebapp/">PPUBS Patent Public Search</a> with our best efforts, shows no trace of Edward Aylward's patent claim.
      He could have been refused, or he might not have filed for a patent afterall.
      We will therefore consider Aylward's publication in the public Hangprinter group as prior art.
    </p>
    <p>
      The conversation received a lot of attention, and the conversation was deleted by a moderator later that day for reasons that are unknown to me.
      Aylward were also blocked from the public group the same day, also for reasons unknown to me.
      I was not the creator of, nor a moderator of, the public Hangprinter group on Facebook.
    </p-->

    <h2>Why I Wrote This Prior Art Presentation</h2>
    <p>
      I think the patent in question is problematic because it's way too general, and covers well known and established knowledge.
      Nothing in the patent fulfills the criteria of being non-obvious to a person having ordinary skill in the art of cable driven robotics.
    </p>
  </post>
</posts>

<!---
  The patent long url:
https://patft.uspto.gov/netacgi/nph-Parser?Sect1=PTO1&Sect2=HITOFF&d=PALL&p=1&u=%2Fnetahtml%2FPTO%2Fsrchnum.htm&r=1&f=G&l=50&s1=11230032.PN.&OS=PN/11230032&RS=PN/11230032

more test printing KokoKaka: https://twitter.com/tobbelobb/status/963030599073255425

Version 2 forum thread: https://reprap.org/forum/read.php?1,738858
Version 3 forum thread: https://reprap.org/forum/read.php?423,792937

Rail-less delta design: https://reprap.org/forum/read.php?1,525804,532222#msg-532222

-->
