<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="blogtemplate.xsl"?>
<posts year="2023">
  <post id="hangprinter_project_83" heading="Simulation and HP5 Work" date="24-9-2025">
    <p>
        So I made a Slideprinter simulation, check it out at <a href="https://hangprinter.org/">hangprinter.org</a>.
    </p>
    <video width="500" controls="true">
      <source src="./bilder/fast_print_simulator.webm" type="video/webm"></source>
    </video>
    <p>
      It's really cool because it really simulates many aspects of a real machine:
      <ul>
        <li>I wrote a whole library to simulate the lines. Check out <a href="https://github.com/tobbelobb/hp-sim5/">hp-sim5</a>. This has been a grueling multi month effort.</li>
        <li>The simulation is a state of the art XPBD time loop, so close to physical reality.</li>
        <li>The move commands comes from real Klipper, with a real Hangprinter config</li>
        <li>Klipper can stream commands to the simulaton too (if a real mcu is attached).</li>
        <li>The simulated steppers can loose steps, their torque varies with speed etc.</li>
        <li>Spools can be clicked, grabbed and pulled with your mouse of touch screen.</li>
        <li>Simulation can be speed up considerably compared to realtime.</li>
        <li>The logo print simulation simulates millions of individual step-signals and micrograms of disposed material.</li>
        <li>It's imlpemented both in Javascript and in Python.</li>
        <li>The whole machine and its simulation scene and config is described in a file format called USD, see <a href="https://github.com/tobbelobb/hp-sim5/blob/main/examples/usd_scenes/slideprinter.usda">slideprinter.usda</a>, which enables us to be data-driven, but also compatibility with various 3d modelling, reinforcement learning, and simulation softwares such as Blender and Isaac Sim.</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <p>
      I think simulations are most important part of the Hangprinter Project.
      I'd like to automate the hardware design and fw configuration.
      We just now became able to quantify comparisons between Hangprinter hardware+config setups.
      Just measure how close the tool head is to an optimal route at all times, compared to the exact positions in the gcode file.
      Optimize over CAD parameters and config values, and write a simple cost function.
    </p>
    <p>
      So I'll keep focusing on simulation, not hardware.
      But it's good to have ideas of cost regardless, especially since we have to integrate tightly with a firmware in order to simulate.
      The firmware implies ceirtain hardware which implies cost.
    </p>
    <h2>Cost Estimates</h2>
    <p>
      I computed some BOM cost estimates for various alternatives for the HP5 today. It includes three versions I've been thinking about.
      All cost estimates assume Swedish taxes and shipping, plus a 10% inflation in all prices since 2021.
    </p>
    <div id="spreadsheet-container"></div>
    <style>
      #spreadsheet-container {
        overflow-anchor: none;
        overscroll-behavior: contain;
      }
      #spreadsheet-container2 {
        overflow-anchor: none;
        overscroll-behavior: contain;
      }
      #spreadsheet-container3 {
        overflow-anchor: none;
        overscroll-behavior: contain;
      }
    </style>
    <link href="https://unpkg.com/tabulator-tables@5.6.1/dist/css/tabulator.min.css" rel="stylesheet"></link>
    <script type="text/javascript" src="https://unpkg.com/tabulator-tables@5.6.1/dist/js/tabulator.min.js"></script>


    <h3>Baseline v5 (Roughly HP Performance)</h3>
    <script>
      const rowFormatter2 = function(row) {
        const data = row.getData();
      };

      const table2 = new Tabulator("#spreadsheet-container", {
        nestedFieldSeparator: "|",
        height: "778px",
        layout: "fitDataFill",
        placeholder: "Loading...",

        ajaxURL: "./blog/2025/hangprinter_v5_boms_baseline_v5.json",

        columns: [
          {title: "Item", field: "Item", headerFilter: "input", resizable: false},
          {title: "Quantity", field: "Quantity", headerFilter: "input", resizable: false},
          {title: "Price_SEK", field: "Price_SEK", headerFilter: "input", resizable: false},
          {title: "Price_USD", field: "Price_USD", headerFilter: "input", resizable: false},
        ],

        rowFormatter: rowFormatter2,
      });
    </script>
    <p>
      This is the machine that the HP4 prototype was always meant to be. ODrive S1 boards, Motion tracking with Arducam, Duet3 6XD board etc.
      <b>Cost:</b> 2500 USD
    </p>
    <p>
      <b>Software work required:</b> We'd need to implement the Duet CAN Protocol in the ODrive firmware, which is hard, and the machine will be useless until it's done.
      We could dodge this hard sw work with 5 x 1XD boards, but that brings total cost up by 384 USD, to 2840 USD and defeats some of the purpose with the HP5/HP Performance.
    </p>
    <h3>Duet HCL Nema v5 (Roughly HP Convenience)</h3>
    <p>
      The smallest change to get away from BLDC and ODrive, dodging protocol implementation work and cost, sacreficing performance.
      The 5 x ODrive S1s are swapped with Duet's closed loop stepper drivers (https://www.duet3d.com/duet-3-expansion-1hcl), and the 5 x BLDC motors are swapped for a standard set of Nema17 motors.
      <b>Cost:</b> 1750 USD
      If we skip the encoders for this option, cost is down to ca 1600 USD.
    </p>
    <p>
      <b>Software work required:</b> We would need to do implement torque mode in the expansion board and Duet CAN Protocol. That shouldn't be too hard, and the machine can be useful without it as well.
    </p>
    <h3>Klipper Driven HP5 (Roughly HP Core)</h3>
    <p>
      No closed loop control, no torque mode.
      The Duet3, the 5 x ODrive S1s, and the 5 x BLDC motors are swapped with 5 microcontroller units and 5 Nema17 motors.
      The 5 microcontroller units will be driven by Klipper running on the Raspberry Pi 5 via CAN and a USB to CAN bridge. Also, include one load sensor per anchor is included in this Klipper driven version.
      <b>Cost:</b> 1050 USD
      Adding closed loop to the Klipper Driven HP5 could come as cheap as 5x20 = 100 USD (https://www.ebay.com/itm/126266631121) bringing total cost up to 1150 USD.
    </p>
    <p>
      <b>Software work required:</b> A lot. Klipper's Hangprinter support is very basic. But although its a lot of work, none of the work is very hard, since it's mainly re-implementation into Python,
      and we have the simulator to quickly test everything. The machine is potentially useful even without software upgrades, since the basic Hangprinter support in Klipper already does work.
    </p>
    <h3>Thoughts</h3>
    <p>
      The Duet options might still make sense for those who need performance and with the minimal changes compared to something that has been built proven to work (the HP4 prototype).
      The Klipper option makes most sense to work on for people who want to go cheap and develop, and still maintain the possibility of adding performance later.
    </p>
  </post>
</posts>
